<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Virgin Maries life Faithfully gathered out of auncient and holie fathers. Togeather with meditations and documents vpon the same. Writen first in Italien by the reuerend father Lucas Pinelli, of the Societie of Iesus. And now translated in to English by R.G.</title>
            <author>Pinelli, Luca, 1542-1607.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09670</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19940</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106100</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841825</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841825</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6438</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09670)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6438)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 581:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Virgin Maries life Faithfully gathered out of auncient and holie fathers. Togeather with meditations and documents vpon the same. Writen first in Italien by the reuerend father Lucas Pinelli, of the Societie of Iesus. And now translated in to English by R.G.</title>
                  <author>Pinelli, Luca, 1542-1607.</author>
                  <author>Gibbons, Richard, 1550?-1632.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 104 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Laurens Kel[lam] with priulege,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Doway :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.C.IIII. [1604]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The title page is engraved.</note>
                  <note>R.G. = Richard Gibbons.</note>
                  <note>Name of printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary, --  Blessed Virgin, Saint --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6438:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6438:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE VIRGIN MARIES LIFE,</hi> Faithfully gathered out of auncient and holie fathers,</p>
                  <p>TOGEATHER WITH MEDITATIONS AND DOC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VMENTS <hi>VPON</hi> THE
<hi>SAME.</hi> Writen first in Italian by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend father LVCAS PINELLI of the Societie of IESVS.</p>
                  <p>And now tranſlated in to Engliſh by R. G.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Ec. <hi>24.</hi> verſ. <hi>20.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>As cynnamon and aromatical balme haue I giuen an odour.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AT DOWAY BY LAVRENS KEL</hi> with Priulege. MDCIIII</p>
                  <p>S IOACHIM</p>
                  <p>S ANNA</p>
                  <figDesc>engraved title page depicting the Virgin Mary and Saints Joachim and Anne</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6438:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6438:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEREND, RELIGIOVS, AND VERTVOVS LADIE, the Ladie Ioane Barkley, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſſe of the Engliſh Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in Bruſſels.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Haue beene ſo bould, Religious and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Madame, as to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect this litle booke to you, and make you a preſent thereof, as one vvorthie to receaue &amp; keepe ſuch a iewel. Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie J ſaie, to receaue it, becauſe of your rare vertu, ſo manie vvayes and yeares vttered to the vvorld, by your both Religious vocation and maners: vvorthie to keepe it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe J knovv right vvel, how much more you doe value and eſteeme ſpiritual, then temporal tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſures.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6438:3"/>
            <p>The tooke, Madame, is in qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie verie ſmal, but in ſubſtance paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing greate. For that it conteineth the life of our bleſſed Ladie, that is, of the moſt excellent, most vvorthie, and moſt holie perſon (Chriſt IESVS her ſonne onlie excepted) that either liued at anie time in this vvorld, or now raigneth glorious in heauen. Jn ſomuch that, al dulie conſidered, for me to commende you this woorke it ſelfe, vvere a thing ſuperfluous: to requeſt you to accept it, vvere a thing needeles: to praie you to take it in your cuſtodie and keepe it, vvere but to make eſtimation of you, farre othervviſe then your godlie &amp; vertuous ſtate doth deſerue.</p>
            <p>This one thing J vvil adde and end therevvithal, that if my ſmal paines taken in the tranſlating of it,
<pb facs="tcp:6438:3"/>may anie vviſe benefit your ſpiritual good and conſolation, and aduance you in the deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Mother of God, I vvil thinke them vvel employed. And ſo deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring as vvel to be remembred in your feruent deuotions, as alſo that this offer, ſuch as it is, may ſerue for vvitnes of my duetiful affection, to further that of your good ſelfe and yours to vvards this mother of mercie and her ſvveete ſonne JESVS, J commend your to them both, and humblye take my leaue: vvishinge you in this vvorld, Madame, al abundance of heauenlie grace and contentement, and in the vvorld to come, euerlaſting felicitie and ioye.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours,</signed>
               <salute>Madame,</salute>
               <signed>in Chriſt Ieſus, to commaunde R. G.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6438:4"/>
            <head>THE A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>THOR TO THE CHRISTIAN AND DEVOVTE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or ſo much as in this moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Cittie of Naples, deuoute Reader, there be manie Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations dedicated to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Virgin, and bleſſed mother of God. which oftentimes did come togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not onlie to praiſe and honour the Queene of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, but alſo to exerciſe them ſelues in mental prayer, a meane moſt effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual, whereby to amend and direct our life, and my Superiours deeming that it would be a greate help to ſuch, as be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voute to the Mother of God, if they might haue an abridgement of her life and actions, both to conſider and imitate them: this there godlie deſire did animate and ſpurre me forwards to write this litle booke, which doth conteine firſt the Storie of the Virgin <hi>Maries</hi> life and manners, faithfullie gathered out of auncient and holy fathers, with the citations of their bookes, which for more briefenes and facilities ſake to find out, the places that be alleaged, at heere ſett downe in latin.</p>
            <p>After this there be imm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>diatly ſet downe
<pb facs="tcp:6438:4"/>for eache hiſtorie, three ſhort points where vppon to meditate, taken out either of the hiſtorie that goeth before, or of ſome other godly conſiderations; to the end that eache one may haue ſufficient matter, whereof to thinke and diſcourſe: becauſe our minde and vnderſtanding, when it hath ſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and grownde, doth eaſelie diſcourſe of it ſelfe, and findeth out diuers conceits and ſpiritual thoughts, in which the ſowle is much comforted, and entring into it ſelfe doth thereby reape great fruite and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie. Finallie after the points of meditation, there doe folow three documents or inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, awnſwering to the ſaid points, which documents put in practiſe, wil ſerue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedlie as a wonderful aide, to direct and conforme our liues and actions, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thoſe of the bleſſed Virgin, our Queene and Soueraigne.</p>
            <p>Maruaile not, Chriſtian Reader, that I in this little booke doe laie, before thine eyes the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> for a patterne to imitate her life &amp; manners? ſeeing that <hi>Sophronius</hi> doth confeſſe the Virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> to be the forme and Rule of Chriſtian diſcipline, giuen by almightie God to men, next after Chriſt the firſt and chiefeſt preſident of al perfection. <hi>Rupertus</hi> likewiſe avowcheth, that our Sauiour Chriſt aſcending vp into
<pb facs="tcp:6438:5"/>heauen, leaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> for a miſtreſſe of Chriſtian beleefe, &amp; life. And long time before them both, that worthie and holie martyr S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> named the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> the miſtreſſe of Chriſtian Religion: which office of miſtreſſe, ſhe did rather performe in woorks &amp; examples of perfect and ſound vertues, then in woords. In ſomuch that who ſoeuer wil conſider with diligence the courſe of the virgin <hi>Maries</hi> life, ſhal euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie perceaue that the prouidence and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God did ſo diſpoſe her life, that it might ſerue for an example to al ſorts of perſon, as I wil manifeſt by the enſuing diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>The Virgin <hi>Marie</hi> from three yeares of her age vntil fourteene, remained with other virgins in the temple of Ieruſalem, in which place, with her abhorring the vanitie of the world, with her prompt Obedience to the Superiours of that place, with her diligence in praier and deuotion, with her modeſtie and humilitie ſhe taught as vvel virgins, as other religious vveomen, how each of them ought to behaue them ſelues in their ſtate and calling. Afterwards til neare fourtie and fiue yeares, ſhe vvas a miſtreſſe to married vveomen, and ſuch as haue care of how ſhold: for albeit ſhe was the Queene of Angels, the mother of God,
<pb facs="tcp:6438:5"/>and ful of al grace and wiſdome, yet ſhe did obey, honour and reſpect her ſpouſe <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> with vvhome ſhe liued alwaies in concord and quietnes. Beſides this, in this care of her houſe and bringing vp of her ſonne Chriſt, ſhe vvas moſt diligent: for ſhe did ſo wel diſpoſe and appoint her time, that neither the affaires of her houſe did hinder her pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, nor theſe vvere anie impediment or let, to ſuch domeſtical buſines as pertained to her charge.</p>
            <p>In the reſt of her life which vvas, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the more common opinion, vntil threeſcore and three yeares of age, ſhe was an example and miſtreſſe to widdowes and poore vveomen, becauſe ſhe in her wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe ſtate, as S. <hi>Brigit</hi> writeth, as it were deade to the world, did liue vvholie to God; &amp; giuen to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>templation of celeſtial things, did leade a life rather diuine than humane. Her prouiſion vvas ſmal and fit for poore folkes, and ſome doe eſteeme that ſhe, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Aſcenſion of Chriſt, did liue as the Hebrew widdowes were wont to doe, of the common almes and collections, vvhich in the primitiue Church were gathered to ſuſtaine the poore. To be ſhort, ſhe taught by her example how euerie one ought to behaue him ſelfe as wel in time of proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and fauour, as of aduerſitie and tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<pb facs="tcp:6438:6"/>for ſomuch as in al the giftes and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours that ſhe receaued at Gods ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, ſhe did humble her ſelfe with al her hart; as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in this, that being choſen the mother of God, &amp; hauing vnderſtoode ſuch newes from the Angel <hi>Gabriel,</hi> ſhe called her ſelfe the ſeruant and hand-maide of our Lorde. And when ſhe went to viſit S. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and vvas by her ſaluted verie magnificallie, and as the mother of God: ſhe did magnifie our Lord, acknowledging al her good to come from him. So that in proſperitie ſhe teacheth vs to humble our ſelues, and to praiſe alinghtie God.</p>
            <p>But in tribulation and aduerſitie ſhe hath giuen vs ſuch rare examples of vertue, that if the afflicted and vexed in this life would wel conſider them, their tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations would not ſeeme to be ſo grieuous as they doe As for example ſake, the Virgin <hi>Marie</hi> in this life had no other good but one onlie ſonne, vvhich was of infinite bountie and perfection, for that he was in one perſon both God and man, now ſhe did ſee this her ſonne to be of enuie accuſed, &amp; vniuſtlie condemned to the moſt grieuous torments that could be imagined, euen to the moſt infamous death of the Croſſe. Shee did ſee him alſo die vppon the Croſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt two theeues, and was not able to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford
<pb facs="tcp:6438:6"/>him the leaſt comfort that could be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed: when not withſtanding ſhe did ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port al theſe iniuries and cruelties, with incredible fortitude of courage, not moued to indignation againſt thoſe enuious accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, not lamenting of the wicked Iewes, nor reproching the Apoſtles that ſo diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie had forſaken their maiſter.</p>
            <p>Yet were the Virgin <hi>Maries</hi> tribulations not ended with this, for that <hi>Artopheius</hi> ſaith after the Aſcenſion of Chriſt, ſhe was greatlie perſecuted of ſome malicious and wicked people, who did vexe and moleſt her by vſing her ſpitefullie in woorks, and detracting of her good name in woords: but ſhe with patience and praying to God for her perſecutours, did ouercome the euil wil of them al. Accept then, good Reader, this ſo perfect a patterne and mirrour of Chriſtian perfection: and I doe exhort thee, if to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e thou canſt take thereby ſome fruite for thy ſoule, not to expect and deffer til to morowe. I doe alſo exhort thee to cleanenes and puritie of minde, which wil make thee fit firſt for meditation, and then to be more beloued and fauoured of the Virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> who hath particular care and protection of thoſe that be chaſte and pure: finallie I doe exhort thee to practiſe thoſe documents that do immediatlie folow the meditations,
<pb facs="tcp:6438:7"/>which documents doe direct vs to doe wel, and to bridle our paſſions and diſordered appetites. For to make goodlie diſcourſes, to find out deepe conceits in meditation, and afterwards not to worke wel according to our good determinations and inſtructions, is euen as if one heard a good ſermon ful of excellent doctrine &amp; holſome counſel, but neuer did practiſe any of al thoſe things he had heard.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6438:7"/>
            <head>THE TRANSLATOR to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Send thee, Benigne Reader, this little Treatiſe of the life of our bleſſed Ladie, vvhich I tranſtated out of Italian into English, as a paune of a bigger bulke concerning the ſame matter, remayning yet in my hands: vvhich ended, vvil giue thee, I hope ſuch ſatisfaction and contentment, touching this point of her life togeather vvith manie other things, as therin may make for the ſpiritual good of thy ſovvle, and further thee exceedinglie in deuotion and dutie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvards the Virgin mother of God and Queene of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, that thou shalt little neede hereafter, if I be not deceaued, to expect anie other diſcourſe of this matter.</p>
            <p>In the meane ſeaſon I doe moſt hartilie requeſt thee, that as this my endeauour doth onlie reſpect thy ſovvles ſpiritual benifite, that God may be glorified in thee, and thou thy ſelfe be ſaued: ſo thou vvillinglie a forde mee, thy praiers to asſiſt mee, as vvel in this vvoorke vvhich I doe promiſe thee, as alſo that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his deuine maieſtie according to my vocation, vve may both at length enioy his euerlaſting glorie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy heartilie affected wel willer. R. G.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="hymn_and_prayer">
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
               <pb facs="tcp:6438:8"/>
               <head>Ad Sanctillimam Virginem-Dei Genitricem Mariam.</head>
               <lg>
                  <head>HYMNVS.</head>
                  <l>AVe ſuprema Virginum,</l>
                  <l>Magni parentis ſilia,</l>
                  <l>Et ſponſa Sacri Flaminis,</l>
                  <l>Chriſtique mater inclyta.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Vestita ſole fulgido,</l>
                  <l>Quae calce lunam ſubteris,</l>
                  <l>Et cincta ſtellis tempora,</l>
                  <l>Splendiſcis intra Regiam.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tu Moſis arca myſtica,</l>
                  <l>Suaue manna continens:</l>
                  <l>Tu clauſus hortus vndique,</l>
                  <l>Turriſque munitiſsima.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tu fortitudo Martyrum,</l>
                  <l>Decuſque Confitentium,</l>
                  <l>Tu Virginum pulcherrima,</l>
                  <l>Regina caelo praeſides.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A te parens mitiſsima,</l>
                  <l>Opem gementes poſcimus,</l>
                  <l>Dulcem praecare ſilium,</l>
                  <l>Vt noſtra tollat crimina.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Summo parenti Caelitum,</l>
                  <l>Magnaeque Proli Virginis,</l>
                  <l>Sancto ſimul Paraclito,</l>
                  <l>Sit ſumma laus &amp; gloria.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
               <pb facs="tcp:6438:8"/>
               <head>℣. Ora pro nobis ſancta Dei genitrix. ℞. Vt digni efficiamur promiſſionibus Chriſti.</head>
               <head type="sub">Oremus.</head>
               <p>Concede nos famnlos tuos, quaeſumus Domine Deus, perpetua mentis &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris ſanitate gaudere: &amp; glorioſa beatae Mariae ſemper Virginis interceſsione, a prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenti liberari tristitia, &amp; aeterna perfrui lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titia. Per Dominum noſtrum Ieſum Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum filium tuum, qui &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <head>To the moſt holie <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God Marie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <head>An Himne.</head>
                  <l>HAile of al Virgins the moſt high,</l>
                  <l>Daughter of father eminent,</l>
                  <l>And of the holie Ghoſt the ſpouſe,</l>
                  <l>Of Chriſt the mother excellent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Clodde with the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne that ſhineth bright</l>
                  <l>Thou vnder foote the moone doſt treade,</l>
                  <l>And crowned with a crowne of ſtarres,</l>
                  <l>Iu heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s court ſunne beames doſt ſpreade.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou Ark of Moyſes myſtical,</l>
                  <l>Doſt manna ſweete in thee incloſe,</l>
                  <l>Thou garden ſhut on euerie ſide,</l>
                  <l>And tower that fenced is from foes.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:6438:9"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou art the martyrs fortitude,</l>
                  <l>Of Confeſſors the worthines,</l>
                  <l>Aboue al Virgins faireſt thou,</l>
                  <l>In heauen art Queene Gouernes</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of thee o mother to vs moſt milde.</l>
                  <l>Wee much lamenting ſuccour craue:</l>
                  <l>Praie to thy ſweete ſonne that he,</l>
                  <l>Our ſinnes to toke awaie vouchſaue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To higheſt father of al Saincts,</l>
                  <l>To the great ſonne of Virgin free.</l>
                  <l>Likewiſe vnto the holie Ghoſt.</l>
                  <l>Moſt vvorthie praiſe and glorie bee.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <head>℣. Praie for vs o holie mother of God. ℞. That vve may be made vvorthie of the promiſes of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let vs pray.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>GRaunt vs thy ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, we beſeche thee o Lord, to enioy perpetual health of mind and bodie: and by the glorious inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the euer bleſſed virgin MARIE, to be deliured from this preſent ſorowe, &amp; to enioy euerlaſting gladnes. Through our Lord IESVS Chriſt thy ſonne, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth and reigneth, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="biography">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6438:9"/>
               <head>THE HISTORIE OF the virgin Maries Conception. 1</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Virgin MARIES conceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was of twoe ſortes. One was eternal in the minde of God; when he did chooſe her to be mother of the Sauiour of the world, &amp; allot her the moſt excellent giftes, that could be imparted to anie pure creature: wherefore<note n="a" place="margin">Trag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d de Christ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> patiente.</note> 
                  <hi>Nazianze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> ſaith, that no creature can be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> who ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounteth al in grace and perfection: An other conception, was temporal in the wombe of her mother S. <hi>Anne,</hi> in the yeare after the creation of the world according to<note n="b" place="margin">In cap. <hi>2.</hi> Matth queſtio. <hi>91</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Abulenſis,</hi> three thouſand, nine hundred fourtie &amp; ſix. <hi>Ioachim</hi> was her father, and both her parents were noble no leſſe of linage
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6438:10"/>then vertue:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> contrar Colyr. haer. <hi>70.</hi> Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ho. li. <hi>1.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſt. cap <hi>7.</hi> Niſſen. de humana Christi ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neratione.</note> who as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> and others do recount, albeit they were old, &amp; liued manie yeares in wedlocke without yſſue, yet becauſe they had great hope in god, &amp; had alſo vowed to conſecrate vnto him the child they were to haue, they did not ceaſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund the ſame of our Lord continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie, with praiers, faſtings, and almes. For ſo we read in<note n="d" place="margin">Tomo.
<hi>4.</hi> de natiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate B. vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginis.</note> S. <hi>Hieroms</hi> works, that yearelie they deuided their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance into three partes, giuing one to the Temple, and miniſters thereof; an other to poore folkes, and pilgrimes: and reſeruing the third part for them ſelues.<note n="r" place="margin">Beda in martyrolo.</note> Finallie after twentie yeares paſt they obtained the deſired fauour: for the eight of December S. <hi>Anne</hi> conceaued our euer B. virgin <hi>Marie.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Conſider how god, chooſing the virgin
<hi>Marie</hi> for the mother of his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie begotten ſonne, did adorne her with great perfection, his cuſtome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to beſtow grace and habilitie vpon eache one, according to the office and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6438:10"/>dignitie he doth giue him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Conſider how the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> was alſo preſerued from original ſinne, for ſo much as god was able to doe it, and that he ſhould doe ſo, it was not onlie conuenient, but likewiſe did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounde to the honour of Chriſt, to haue a mother that nether ſhould be enimy to god, nor ſubiect to the diuel as al thoſe are, that be conceaued in original ſinne.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Conſider how S. <hi>Anne,</hi> which was great with childe, did feele maruelous effects, becauſe the grace of the virgin
<hi>Marie</hi> was ſo paſſing excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that it redounded alſo to her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Thruſt not thy ſelfe into offices &amp; dignities, for god doth giue grace to thoſe, whome he hath elected &amp; cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, to preeminencie.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 If original ſinne doe make a man ſubiect to the diuel, and an enimie to god, what wil actual ſinne doe? flie it therfore more then death.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:6438:11"/>
                  <p n="3">3. If thou alſo haſt a deſire to feele ſtraunge effects, haue the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> alwaies in thy hart.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>OF THE VIRGIN Maries Natiuitie. 2.</head>
               <p>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Epiph ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tato.</note>EPIPHANIVS and<note n="b" place="margin">Germa. Sermo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> de oblatione Mariae. S. Brigida lib. <hi>1.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelat. ca. <hi>9</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Germanus</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs of Conſtantinople doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, that the virgin <hi>Maries</hi> parents retyring them ſelues, <hi>Ioachim</hi> into a mountaine of the deſert, where he fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted fourtie daies, &amp; <hi>Anne</hi> into a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of hers, there to praye God, that he would vowchſafe to deliuer them from the ignominie of barronnes; an Angel reuealed to <hi>Ioachim</hi> that he ſhould haue a childe, &amp; that <hi>Anne</hi> had now conceaued. And ſo when
<hi>Herod</hi> the Idumean raigned in Iewrie, who by force and vniuſt dealing tooke the roial ſceptre from the tribe of <hi>Iuda,</hi> &amp; was the firſt forren king of the Iews, in which time according to the<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie of <hi>Iacob</hi> the
<hi>Meſsias</hi> was to come euen then the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> was borne
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6438:11"/>to wit<note n="d" place="margin">Abule<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> citat.</note> three thouſand, nine hundred, fourtie &amp; ſeuen yeares after the creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world, the eight daie of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember, and this not without myſterie: for that in the ſame moneth, as the Iewiſh tradition doth make mention, <hi>Eue</hi> was created by God in the terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrial paradiſe<note n="e" place="margin">in ca. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Ioan.</note> 
                  <hi>Theophilactus</hi> and
<hi>Euthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minius</hi> doe write that <hi>Marie</hi> was the onlie daughter of
<hi>Anne,</hi> who neuer had anie other huſband than <hi>Ioachim;</hi> nether had one or the other any more children than <hi>Marie.</hi> So that when S.<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>cap</hi> 19</note> 
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> doth cal
<hi>Marie</hi> of <hi>Cleophas,</hi> ſiſter of oure <hi>Marie</hi> the virgin, it is to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode that ſhe was her kinſwoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, like as
<hi>Sara</hi> ſaid ſhe was <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, that is, allied to him.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Conſider the ioy the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> brought to her parents, by her natiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; who, as we may thinke, did with great deuotion offer her vp to God, as ſoone as ſhe was borne.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Contemplate how this celeſtial &amp; heauenlie dawning, with her birth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6438:12"/>giuing ioy to heauen &amp; earth doth end the obſcure night of damnation, and begin the happie day of ſaluation.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Behould how <hi>Marie</hi> is that houſe, in vvhich the king of eternal glorie was to repoſe, builded by god for his owne vſe: who wanting nether wiſdome to diſpoſe the ſame in the beſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner, nor power to adorne it, we ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that ſhe had al perfection poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 If thou acknowledge whatſoeuer good thou haſt, to come from god; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that the ſame ſhal be alwaies bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp; more perfected in thee by him, thou ſhalt alſo receaue much more.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 If thou through ſinne ſhalt become blind, or through paſſion feeble in the eyes of thy vnderſtanding, thou ſhalt not enioie the dawning, &amp; much leſſe the ſonne: that is to ſay thou ſhalt be depriued of the virgin <hi>Maries</hi> fauoure, &amp; of the grace of <hi>Christ</hi> her ſonne.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thou maiſt alſo be the repoſing place of god, if yet nether ſinne, nor
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6438:12"/>vanitie of the world doe dwel in thee, which both be odious to him.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>OF THE VIRGIN Maries Preſentation in the Temple.
<hi>3.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHen the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> was three yeares old,
<hi>Ioachim</hi> and <hi>Anne</hi> according as they had vowed, did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent her to the Prieſts of the Temple, who as<note n="a" place="margin">Euod ſua epis Eccleſia ca</note> 
                  <hi>Euodius</hi> and<note n="b" place="margin">N pho li. cap. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Nicephorus</hi> doe affirme, receaued her as a pretious gift conſecrated to god, to bring her vp with the virgins of the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple.<note n="c" place="margin">De hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſti. genera.</note> 
                  <hi>Nyſſen</hi>ꝰ writeth, that in the Temple there was a ſeparated place, where al thos virgins were trained vp, that were dedicated to god, &amp; that <hi>Marie</hi> remained there, into which place no weomen entred that had bene maried. But<note n="d" place="margin">Orig tract <hi>2</hi> in Ma</note> 
                  <hi>Origenes</hi> &amp;<note n="e" place="margin">Cyril aduerſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Anth. morp. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Cyrillus Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>drinus</hi> doe ſay that
<hi>Marie,</hi> after ſhe had brought forth Chriſt, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred there alſo as a virgin: a thing which the Iewes reprehended, but <hi>Zacharie</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:6438:13"/>father to Iohn Baptiſt defended the ſame, who knew the myſterie of the virgins childbirth,<note n="f" place="margin">Euod. cit.</note> 
                  <hi>Marie</hi> dwelt in the Temple twelue yeares, and<note n="g" place="margin">Cedren in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pend. hiſtor.</note>
                  <hi>Cedrenus</hi> ſaieth that ſhe went not forth from thence, except it were for ſome neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie to her coſen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> which did make her aboade neere the Temple: moreouer<note n="h" place="margin">Nicom. homil de oblat. virg</note> 
                  <hi>Georgius Nicomedienſis</hi> doth ſaie, and<note n="i" place="margin">Ambroſ lib. 2 de
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>irg.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> confirmeth it, that the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> was in that place often viſited by the Angel. In the eight yeare that ſhe remained in the Temple, which was the eleue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th from her age according to<note n="k" place="margin">Cedre cit. &amp; Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſ. de B. Maria lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap.
<hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Cedrenus,</hi> ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came orphane by the death of her parents.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Conſider the diligence of <hi>Ioachim</hi> and
<hi>Anne</hi> in fulfilling their vow, for as ſoone as <hi>Marie</hi> was weaned, they did preſent her to the Prieſts of the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Conſider how the Prieſts were comforted to ſee the little virgin <hi>Marie</hi> ſo modeſt and deuoute, and how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired by God, they receaued her with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6438:13"/>particular guſt &amp; reuerence, as a moſt holie pledge, to bring her vp amongſt the other virgins of the Temple.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Conſider the deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with which the virgin
<hi>Marie</hi> did offer her ſelfe wholie to God, and what content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhe did feele in her hart, being to paſſe her childhood, ſeparated from the vnquietnes of the world, in a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie place, and with holie exerciſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Not to ſatisfie a vowe made, or to deffer the ſame without lawful cauſe, the one, and the other, doth diſpleaſe God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Haue great reſpect to ſuch things as be dedicated to God, becauſe he eſteemeth the honour, or contempt done to them, as done to him ſelfe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thou ſhalt liue alwayes diſcomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, if thou do not ſeperate thy ſelfe, at leaſt with this affection, from the tranſitorie things of the world.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:6438:14"/>
               <head>OF THE <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IRGIN Maries life in the Temple. 4.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANdreas Cretenſis</hi> doth write that the virgin
<hi>Marie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itione
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e pa.</note> whiles ſhe dwelt in the Temple amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the virgins, did ſo giue her ſelfe to learning, that ſhe vnderſtoode verie wel the lawe &amp; the Prophets.<note n="b" place="margin">Lib <hi>2.</hi> cemp. ca. &amp; lib.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. cap.
<hi>4</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Sabellicus</hi> doth report, that ſhe diuided the daie-time in this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. In the morning, for three houres ſpace, ſhe gaue her ſelfe to prayer &amp; deuotion, from thence foorth, vntil middaie, ſhe ſate at her woorke with the other virgins, &amp; that for the moſt part ſpining; after dinner ſhe did reade the holie ſcripture.<note n="c" place="margin">Lib. 1. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l cap. <hi>10</hi> &amp; lib. <hi>3.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>p <hi>8.</hi> Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tin. lib. <hi>7</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arca.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uho. ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t. cap. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note>S. Bright ſeeteth downe verie largelie the manners and cuſtomes of the virgin
<hi>Marie</hi> in her youth, and amongſt others relateth theſe: She contemned riches and wealth, in ſo much that what ſhe could get, ſhe gaue to the poore; She tooke delight in nothing but in god; She
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6438:14"/>did willinglie and often talke of the future
<hi>Meſsias;</hi> ſhe did with drawe her ſelfe, as much as ſhee could, from worldlie diſcourſes; ſhe did force her bodie, of which the Angels had care, to be obedient in al things to the ſoule: ſhe was ſo comelie and modeſt, that ſhe moued to deuotion ſuch as did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold her.<note n="d" place="margin">In co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend. h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stor &amp; Caniſ. li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cap.
<hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Cedrenus</hi> doth recount that at twelue yeares of age, being at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night in prayer, ſhe heard theſe words <hi>Thou shalt bring foorth my Sonne,</hi> the which ſhe did not manifeſt to anie ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the world, vntil Chriſt was aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into heauen.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Contemplate how the vigin <hi>Marie,</hi> al the time ſhe did dwel amongſt the virgins of the Temple, was a liuelie pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of perfection, becauſe ſhe did in euerie thing obſerue her ſelfe, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king alwaies in the preſence of god.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Conſider how the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> for her modeſt holines and wiſdome, was beloued of al her companions, and eſteemed as theire miſtreſſe, ſo that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6438:15"/>they had recourſe to her for comfort and counſel, and ſhe did moſt kindlie receaue, comfort, and helpe them.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Conſider how al the virgins of the Temple did beare great reuerence to the virgin <hi>Marie:</hi> to whome ſhe was not onlie a mirrour of vertue, but did her beſt to inſtruct them in perfection, and when neede was, to pacifie &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. If in al things thou wilt obſerue thy ſelf, procure with the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> to be alwaies in Gods preſence.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. To be loued and eſteemed for anie other reſpect, then for vertue &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, is a thing that dureth little, and is leſſe worth.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Good ſpeeche, accompanied with good example, doth edifie, but with il example, it deſtroieth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:6438:15"/>
               <head>OF THE <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IRGIN Maries ſpouſage vvith S. Ioſeph. 5.</head>
               <p>VVHen the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> was four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene yeares old, the Prieſts of the Temple, as<note n="a" place="margin">In ora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> de nati. Domini.</note> 
                  <hi>Niſſenus</hi> doth recount ſent her to her kinsfolkes in <hi>Nazareth,</hi> that according to the cuſtome, ſhe might be maried, becauſe in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple they did not treate of matrimonie, and ſome litle while after, by aduiſe of the ſaid Prieſts, ſhe was deſpouſed to <hi>Ioſeph</hi> a iuſt man, who was of the ſame countrie, and Tribe, that <hi>Marie</hi> was.<note n="b" place="margin">De per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. virg. Mariae.</note> 
                  <hi>Hugo de Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cto Victore</hi> writeth that the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> did conſent to the matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, becauſe ſhe vnderſtoode that ſuch was Gods vvil, &amp; knevv likewiſe by reuelation, that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> would liue moſt chaſt with her. Concerning the vow of virginitie that <hi>Marie</hi> did make, although<note n="c" place="margin">Quidan Scholaſti &amp; Brig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>da cit.</note> ſome ſay ſhe made it with condition, if it ſo pleaſed God, yet <hi>S.</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Thom.
<hi>3.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> q. <hi>28.</hi> ar.</note> 
                  <hi>Thomas,</hi> with<note n="e" place="margin">Auguſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> de ſancta virgini.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>S. Auguſtin</hi> doth hold,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6438:16"/>that ſhe, before ſhe was deſpouſed had purpoſed virginitie, and after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie contracted vvith her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, both of common conſent did vow perpetual virginitie.<note place="margin">Historie</note> But be it howſoeuer, yet two things are here certaine. One is, that the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> before ſhe was announced by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, had vowed virginitie, as <hi>f</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhal be declared. An other we haue out of <hi>Bede,</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Bed. ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e annun. &amp; ſerm.
<hi>4.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e aſſump. Ruper. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>b. <hi>3.</hi> in
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ant.</note>
                  <hi>Rupertus,</hi> &amp;<note n="i" place="margin">Abd. in
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ta S. Bar
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>olom.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aniſ. li. <hi>2.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>p. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Abdias,</hi> to wit, that from the creation of the world, the virgin
<hi>Marie</hi> was the firſt amongſt vvoemen, that by perpetual vow did conſecrate her virginitie to god.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Contemplate how god ordeined the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> ſhould take a husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, to deliuer her from the ſuſpicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world, if vnmaried ſhe had brought forth Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Contemplate how <hi>Marie</hi> though ſhee did farre exceede her ſpouſe <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in wiſdome, vertue and holines, yet did ſhee beare him reſpect and honour
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6438:16"/>him as her ealder, conſidering in his perſon god, who had giuen her him.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Contemplate how the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> neuer leauing her deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al moſt diligent in gouernment of her howſe: in ſo much that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was aſtomed at it, and did alſo beare her great reuerence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Seeing that god is a moſt wiſe Lord, if thou be not more then proud, thow muſt by the virgin <hi>Maries</hi> exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, approue and execute whatſoeuer he doth ordaine.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 If thou do not honour thy elders, thou wilt diſpleaſe god, and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thy ſelfe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Temporal exerciſes muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comodated, as much as is poſſible, to thoſe that be ſpiritual, ſo that theſe be not hindered nor diſturbed by the others.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:6438:17"/>
               <head>OF THE VIRGIN Maries Annunciation. 6.</head>
               <p>FOuere moneths, ſaith<note n="a" place="margin">In epist.</note>
                  <hi>Euodius,</hi> after that the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> was deſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, God ſent to her the Angel <hi>Gabriel,</hi> who as<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſic ca, <hi>18</hi> Hier. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>iſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ad
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſtochiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. hom.
<hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> &amp;c <hi>Hierome</hi> write, entred to the virgin in a mans ſhape, ſhe then being recollected as d <hi>S. Bernard</hi> ſaith in her cloſet at prayer: he ſaluted her; &amp; ſaid that ſhe was to conceaue &amp; beare the Sauiour of the world.<note n="e" place="margin">B. virg. cap. <hi>1.</hi> Anſel.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om. intra it IESVS Auguſt.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſancta
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>irgine ca.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Saint Luke</hi> telleth how the virgin hearing her ſelfe ſaluted with ſo great praiſe; was troubled thereat, and afterwards asked how that might be done, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe knewe not man: that is as f <hi>Holie</hi> fathers doe expound it, ſhe had vowed neuer to know man, but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſtil a virgin, to whom the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel aunſwering did ſaie, that it ſhould be done by woorke of the holy Ghoſt, without violating either vowe or vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gintie. Then the virgin did humblie
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6438:17"/>giue her conſent, to what ſoeuer god did commaund her.<note n="g" place="margin">In Litu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Chryſostom</hi> wil that the word was incarnate, when the Angel ſaid, our Lord is with thee. But<note n="h" place="margin">Augu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> de fide a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Petr. ca <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> and<note n="i" place="margin">Damaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> de fide or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. lib.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Damaſcene</hi> doe think, that it tooke fleſh when the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
<hi>Marie</hi> did giue her conſent, <hi>Behold the handmayde of our Lord, be it done to me according to thy vvorde.</hi> Now when the Angel had thus ended his embaſſage, and giuen newes to the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> that alſo
<hi>Elizabeth</hi> had by gods wil conceaued in her old age, he depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſhe folowed on her praier.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plate how the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> deſiring to be ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the <hi>Meſsias</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; requeſting this at gods hands: the Angel came to her, who ſaluting her with humble reuerence, did cal her ful of grace, and bleſſed among weomen.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Contemplate how the virgin hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing her ſelfe ſaluted in ſuch manner,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as troubled: &amp; thinking what kind of ſalutation this might be, the Angel
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6438:18"/>told her, how ſhe was choſen of god, for mother of his ſonne the Meſias.</p>
                  <p n="3">Comtemplate how vnderſtanding alſo that ſhe ſhould be both a mother and virgin, ſhe did not waxe proude by reaſon of ſo great dignitie, but did hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble her ſelfe ſaying, <hi>Behold the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayde of our Lord, be it done to me</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he ordeineth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 If thou wilt be exalted of God, procure by the example of the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> that thy humilitie come in deede from thy hart.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Do not thou ſeeke nor reioyce to be praiſed of men, ſeeing the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> was troubled whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe was prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the Angel.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 If thou deſire that thy ſoule be precious and beautiful to the eyes of our Lord, adorne the ſame with cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie and humilitie as <hi>Marie</hi> did hers.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:6438:18"/>
               <head>OF THE <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IRGIN Maries viſiting Elizabeth. 7.</head>
               <p>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Lucae. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>VVhen the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> had vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode of the Angel, how God had ſo fauoured <hi>Elizabeth</hi> that ſhe had conceaued, notwithſtanding her barre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes and old age, riſing from her praier ſhe went to viſit her, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce with her of the fauour beſtowed vpon her. In vvhich voyage, although it vvere painful, becauſe it was tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough mountaines, and long, for that from <hi>Nazareth</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhe departed, it was three daies iourneie to the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of Ieruſalem, as<note n="b" place="margin">In Lucae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Bede</hi> and S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> do vvrite, where <hi>Zacharie</hi> made his aboade: yet<note n="c" place="margin">Serm<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> de verbis A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocal.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Bernard</hi> ſaith that the virgin going thither, did not feele that vvearines, which weomen ar ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to feele after they haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, becauſe that which ſhe had conceaued was not humane but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine.<note n="d" place="margin">Lucae. cap <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> Arriued that ſhe was to <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:6438:19"/>houſe ſhe did greete <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and her ſalutation was of ſuch force, that euen the infant in
<hi>Elizabeths</hi> vvombe did leape for ioye. The virgin <hi>Marie</hi> remained there about three moneths.<note n="e" place="margin">In Lucae.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ap. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Theophilactus</hi> doth vvrite, that ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from thence, before
<hi>Elizabeth</hi> was deliuered of her child, &amp; <hi>S. Luke</hi> doth ſeeme to inſinuate this, partlie becauſe it was not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient that vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins ſhould be preſent at womens deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie, partlie alſo for that manie came thither to ſee the miraculous child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birth of
<hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">homil.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>duent. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; Caniſ. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Euſebius Emiſenus</hi> ſaith that al thoſe of <hi>Zacharies</hi> houſe had taken ſo great affection towards the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> that they remained extreme ſorie at her departure.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>template how the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> when ſhe had giuen thankes to our Lord for the benifit beſtowed vpon her, went to viſit and ſerue her coſen, <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> in which voyage we maye wel thinke, that manie ſquadrons of Angels did accompanie their King &amp; Queene</p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:6438:19"/>
                  <p n="2">2 Conſider how at the going of this ſacred arke,
<hi>Zacharies</hi> houſe was bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, for that <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was repleiniſhed with the holie Ghoſt, and Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt was ſanctified in her wombe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was borne.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Contemplate how <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied that the mother of god with ſo ſo great humilitie and charitie did come to her, crying out did praiſe her, but the virgin with a holy canticle did magnifie our Lord, referring al her good and praiſe to him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 How much thou art exalted of god ſo much more oughteſt thou, by the example of the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> to ſubmit thy ſelfe, for the loue of him, to thy neighbour.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Doſt thou deſire to enriche thy ſoule? Seeke to conuerſe with thoſe that be holie and acceptable to god.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 To glorie of ſuch things as be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in thy praiſe, or not to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the good thou haſt receaued, to come from God, is nought els but to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6438:20"/>ſteale from god, that which is his.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>OF THE VIRGIN Marie ſuſpected of Ioſeph. 8.</head>
               <p>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Matth.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>THe virgin <hi>Marie</hi> being returned from <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to her houſe in
<hi>Nazareth,</hi> and now great with childe for three moneths, and
<hi>Ioſeph</hi> not knowing what had paſt betwixt the Angel
<hi>Gabriel</hi> &amp; her, he began to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect: on the one ſide he ſaw the virgin in al her actions reſemble holines and chaſtitie, and knew likewiſe that ſhe had vowed virginitie: on the other ſide he beheld her great with childe, and ſawe that ſhe held her peace, not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him acquainted with the matter, wherfore douting whether this were a thing done by god, or ſome humane weakenes, he reſolued not to accuſe her to the Iudges, nor diffame her, but to depart from her. And as he was thinking of the matter, the Angel ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to him in ſleepe, and told him
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6438:20"/>that he ſhould not feare to abide with the virgin, becauſe ſhe had conceaued by woorke of the holie Ghoſt, and ſhould bring forth a ſonne that ſhould be called IESVS, who ſhould ſaue his people from theire ſinnes.<note n="b" place="margin">Orig. ſer.
<hi>1.</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diuerſis.</note> 
                  <hi>Origen</hi> and<note n="c" place="margin">Bernar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Hom
<hi>2.</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> B. Maria</note> 
                  <hi>S. Bernard</hi> do hold that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued the virgins greatnes with child to be ſome diuine thing, and that he thought him ſelfe vnworthie, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in the companie of ſo holie and vertuous a perſon, and therefore did thinke to depart from her.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Conſider how <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſeing the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
<hi>Marie</hi> with childe, and not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the manner, remained aſtonied &amp; confounded: and becauſe he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies knowen her to be verie holy he reſolued to leaue her ſecreatlie, &amp; ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leade a Pilgrims life abroad in the world, then to accuſe or diffame her.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>template how the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> not knowing whether it were the wil of god, ſhe ſhould diſcouer the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie to her ſpouſe, did rather chooſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6438:21"/>to let this ſuſpition runne of her ſelfe, then to diſcloſe it, hauing yet firſt commended the matter to god in her prayer.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Contemplate how theſe two mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried perſons, being ſo troubled &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, god by an Angel reuealed to <hi>Ioſeph</hi> the myſterie of the Incarnation, done in the virgin by woorke of the holie ghoſt, where vpon both parties did humblie giue thanks to our Lord.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Learne of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> rather to ſuffer, then to diffame thy neighbour.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 It is better to conceale the fauours of god, which make for our praiſe, as the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> did, then to diuulge them eaſelie.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 How much leſſe thou art culpable and worthie of blame, ſo much the more willingly accept of tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which if they be not to purge thy faulte, wil ſerue to increaſe thy glorie.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:6438:21"/>
               <head>OF THE VIRGIN Maries Childbirth. 9.</head>
               <p>VVHen the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared ſome clothes for her litle childe, according to her pouertie, and the time of her deliuerie began to drawe neare, there came forth, ſaith<note n="a" place="margin">Cap.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> S. <hi>Luke,</hi> an edict from <hi>Caeſar Auguſtus,</hi> that the whole world ſhould be enrol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, for euery one to paie tribute in his countrie, wherefore the virgin
<hi>Marie</hi> and <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> went from <hi>Nazareth</hi> to the cittie of <hi>Dauid</hi> called <hi>Bethlem,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were of the houſe and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie of <hi>Dauid.</hi> The voyage was verie noiſome to the virgin, for that it was in winter, through mountaines, and neere foure daies long. Being come to <hi>Bethelem,</hi> they founde al the Innes ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp, ſo that they were forced to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire them ſelues into a ſtal, where the bleſſed virgin in the night was deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of her ſonne Chriſt IESVS,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6438:22"/>god and man. In which childbirth.<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rat.
<hi>1.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Nyſſenus</hi> and<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erm.
<hi>4.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>igil.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>iu. Do
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. virg.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Bernard</hi> do auouche that the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> felt no paine nor trauel at al, but exceeding ioye and comfort<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>4.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Mariae</note> 
                  <hi>S. Amhroſe</hi> and<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>4.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>pr.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m de
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>S. Ildephon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> do adde alſo, that the virginal cloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre of our Ladie did remaine entire and whole.<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ierom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> likewiſe and<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cae. ca. Caniſ. <hi>2.</hi> ca
<hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>S. Hierome</hi> do teache vs, that there was no Midwife preſent, but the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin her ſelfe was both Midwife and Nourſe. The Sheepheards, who had bene warned by the Angels, that ſung <hi>Glorie in the higheſt to God,</hi> came to the ſtal, and with great humilitie and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion adored the holie infant.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Conſider how the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> &amp;
<hi>Ioſeph,</hi> to obey the Emperours edict, went with great trauel towards
<hi>Bethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> where finding none that would lodge them, they retired them ſelues into a ſtal.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Contemplate how there in the night, the virgin feeling an exceeding Iubilie of hart, lifted vp her minde to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6438:22"/>god, and being wholie rauiſhed in him brought forth without paine her ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne Chriſt our Lord.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Contemplate how the virgin, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the diuine fruite of her wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be did with humilitie adore it as her god, and afterwards obteined of him li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to touch him, did with mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie loue take him in her armes, giuing him her virgin breaſt, and milke to ſucke.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Behold how the virgin doth not murmure at the Princes order, nor la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe that did not lodge her, do thou the like, when for lodge her, do thou the like, when for obſeruing the commaundements of God thou muſt needs ſuffer.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Doſt thou deſire to do manie good woorks without wearines and paine? do them willinglie and for the loue of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Then wil Chriſt become thine, when thou ſhalt vſe him as the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> did, with humilitie and loue.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:6438:23"/>
               <head>OF THE VIRGIN Maries Purification. 10.</head>
               <p>AS ſoone as fourtie daies were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the virgins
<hi>Purification</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her deliuerie,<note place="margin">Lucae.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 2.</note> ſhe went to the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in Ieruſalem to offer her ſonne, &amp; giue as the law ordained a paire of turtles or two young pigeons, albeit (as diuers holie b fathers do ſaie) the virgin was not bound to anie ſuch law,<note place="margin">Beda in ca Lucae. Guari.</note> nether needed ſhe purification, for that ſhe had not conceaued by woork of man,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Ser. <hi>2.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione et
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ij.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uitici ca.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> of which yet law maketh expreſſe mention. At that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie time <hi>Simeo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> came into the Temple, who amongſt al the other mothers that were there to be purified, did ſee the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In orat
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Proph.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>meonis.</note>
                  <hi>Marie,</hi> as d <hi>Timotheus</hi> prieſt of Ieruſalem recounteth, enuironed with a wonderful great and diuine light: and ſeeing that other weomen were deſirous to be diſpatched firſt, he ſaid to them: o ye ſeruants, wil you
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6438:23"/>goe before your Ladie and miſtreſſe?<note n="e" place="margin">Cap. <hi>2</hi> Caniſ. li
<hi>4.</hi> ca. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>S. Luke</hi> ſaith that
<hi>Simeon</hi> was a iuſt &amp; religious man, who had receaued an aunſwere from the holie Ghoſt, that before he died he ſhould ſee the
<hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias:</hi> he did ſee him now, &amp; take him in his armes, bleſſing god w th al his hart. And afterwards turning him ſelfe to the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> he tolde her that <hi>Ieſus</hi> ſhould be ſet for a ſigne of contradictions, and that a ſword of ſorowe ſhould pearce her ſoule.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Conſider how the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> though ſhe needed no purification, yet by the example of her ſonne, who was circumciſed, not needing the ſame, would according to the law be puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, leauing thereby, to vs an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of obedience, humilitie and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Conſider with how great mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and deuotion, the virgin entred into the temple, and with how great zeale and ſpiritual feeling, ſhe did of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer both her ſelfe and her ſonne to the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6438:24"/>father of heauen.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Conſider how the virgin hauing heard that dolorus propheſie of <hi>Simeo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> was nothing aſtoined at the matter, as who had wholie reſigned her ſelfe, to gods wil and pleaſure.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Woe to him that is, but wil not ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to be a ſinner, ſeing Chriſt and his mother cared not to be accounted of as ſinners, to obſerue the lawe of god, though in deede they were not ſuch.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Learne of the virgin in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner thou oughteſt to enter &amp; remaine deuoutlie in the Church, which is made to honour god therein.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Put al thy hope in god, and ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proſperitie ſhal lift thee vp to much, nor aduerſitie to much abaſe thee.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:6438:24"/>
               <head>OF THE <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IRGIN Maries flight into AEgipt. 11.</head>
               <p>THe fame of the childe <hi>Ieſus</hi> grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing daily more and more,<note n="a" place="margin">Matt. &amp; Luc. ca. <hi>2.</hi> &amp; Rabanus in
<hi>2.</hi> c. Matth.</note> through the wounderful things which were ſpoken of him, as wel by the ſheepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds touching the reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had from the Angel, as alſo by the Sages concerning the new ſtarre which they had ſeene, and finallie by that which <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Anne</hi> had ſaid in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.<note n="b" place="margin">Chriſoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in <hi>2.</hi> cap. Matth. Auguſt. ſerm de E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piph. &amp; ſerm. de Innocent.</note> 
                  <hi>Herode</hi> as a moſt cruel tyrante, entring into ſuſpition &amp; feare of loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his kingdome, principallie for that the Sages told in Ieruſalem, that he whome they did ſeeke, was borne king of the Iewes: he commaunded that al the children of
<hi>Bethelem</hi> ſhould be murdered, thinking ſo to make Chriſt awaye with the reſt. But god by means of an Angel reuealed al the matter to
<hi>Ioſeph,</hi> ordaining that he ſhould flie into <hi>Aegipt</hi> togeather with the child <hi>Ieſus</hi> and his mother, and
<hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:6438:25"/>with greate diligence did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it. This voiage was much more combreſome then the others paſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was ſo daine and vnexpected, into forren countries, and amongſt barbarous people.<note n="c" place="margin">In ca. <hi>2.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atth.</note>
                  <hi>Anſelmus</hi> and<note n="d" place="margin">Niceph. b. <hi>10.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>31.</hi> et
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ij vt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rt Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>b. <hi>5.</hi> in
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ai. ca. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>9.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>aniſ. lib.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Nicephorus Callyſtus</hi> do recount, how at the entringe of Chriſt into Aegipt, the diuels trembled, and the Idols fel doune to the grounde, not being able to ſtand in the preſence of <hi>Ieſus</hi> who was the true God.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Conſider how the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> to ſaue the litle childe <hi>Ieſus,</hi> whome <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rode</hi> ſought to murder him, was forced to leaue her countrie and frends, and flie into Aegipt, God hauing ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Contemplate how much the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin did endure, in ſo paineful &amp; long a waie, and what griefe her hart did feele, to ſee the litle infant <hi>Ieſus</hi> alſo ſuffer, not hauing, by reaſon of their pouertie, what was neceſſarie for him, nor being able to haue prouided be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6438:25"/>neceſſitie conſtraining them to flie by night, and alſo ſodenlie.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Conſider how the virgin doth not murmour of
<hi>Herodes</hi> crueltie, nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of god, that he doth not deliuer the litle babe from that daunger by ſome other meanes, but ſhe taketh al in good part.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 If tribulation were not a thing profitable, god would not haue ſent it to his ſonne &amp; the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> whom he loued ſo dearelie.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If thou wilt ſuffer nothing in this life, and yet doeſt thinke to haue ioy in the other, thou doeſt deceaue thy ſelfe, becauſe thou deſireſt to be more, then was ether the virgin
<hi>Marie</hi> or <hi>Chriſt</hi> thy Lord.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If in aduerſitie thou doe lament and murmour, thou erreſt, ſhewing thereby to be diſpleaſed with that, which pleaſeth God, and he ſendeth thee for thy good.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:6438:26"/>
               <head>OF THE VIRGIN Maries aboade in Aegipt. 12.</head>
               <p>AFter a long and weariſome way, the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> at the length arriued in the land of <hi>Aegipt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>a</hi> Brocar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptione terrae ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctae in fine.</note> diſtant from
<hi>Bethelem,</hi> whence ſhe departed, twelue long daies iourney. In which voiage it is credible, as<note n="b" place="margin">In con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ca.
<hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ianſenius</hi> ſaith, that the virgin conſumed and ſpent al that, which by Gods inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſhe had reſerued to this end, of the giftes preſented to <hi>Ieſus</hi> by the three Sages. She did ſettle her ſelfe in a place caled <hi>Materea</hi> neare to <hi>Cairo,</hi> for fiue yeares ſpace; in which time, with her owne labour and that of
<hi>Ioſeph</hi> her ſpouſe, they maintained them ſelues, &amp; brought vp <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Ita refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unt, qui id
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iderunt Peregrini</note> In the houſe, where this holie familie, did dwel, remaineth yet a miraculous fountaine of water that ſpringeth vp: there is alſo to be ſeene a little garden, in which time paſt did growe certaine
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6438:26"/>ſmal trees of baulme. In this place, thoſe of Aegipt, to conſerue the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of ſuch holie inhabitants, were wont to keepe a Lampe ſtil burning, vntil the yeare a thouſand, fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and threeſcore. Manie pilgrims likewiſe doe goe thither to viſit that place for deuotion, who al doe tel ſtraunge effects of that water<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſaie it is ſo good, that thoſe called the <hi>Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa</hi> of
<hi>Cairo</hi> doe drinke thereof. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer they doe report, that there is in the ſame place a moſt ſweete ſauour, although the dwelling be now neare fallen downe.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>template how the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> arriued in Aegipt, did finde nether prouiſion made, nor houſe prepared to refreſh her ſelfe after the trauail of her voyage, ſo as we maye thinke that for thoſe firſt nights, ſhe retired her ſelfe to the poore pilgrims lodge.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Contemplate that although the virgin, as a poore ſtraunger, wanted manie things neceſſarie for her, yet
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6438:27"/>did ſhe neuer want her vertues, in ſo much that ſhe neuer did abandon her deuotion, &amp; had diligent care to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for her houſe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Contemplate how the virgin, in al the time of this her baniſhment, did liue verie poorelie: and when com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities wanted for bringing vp her litle babe <hi>Ieſus,</hi> ſhe did ſupplie with her motherlie loue and ſolicitude.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 If thou wilt liue quiet in whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer place, be it neuer ſo incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, thou muſt make ſmal account of thy ſelfe, and be contented with litle as the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> was.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Haue whatſoeuer thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt deſire, yet thou ſhalt neuer be content, vnles thou giue thy ſelfe to the exerciſe of vertue.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Behold how the moſt deare friends of God liue ſparinglie, and ſo beware thou of ſuperfluitie, for it diſpleaſeth God, who hath giuen thee ſuſtinance, and whatſoeuer els that is good.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:6438:27"/>
               <head>OF THE VIRGIN Maries leeſing of Jeſus. 13.</head>
               <p>VVHen <hi>Herode</hi> was once dead, the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> with <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Ieſus</hi> returned to <hi>Nazareth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>a</hi> Matt ca. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel had ordained, who againe appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in ſleepe. From <hi>Nazareth</hi> the virgin went euerie yeare with <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> and <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> at the ſolemne daie of <hi>Paſche,</hi> to adore in the Temple of
<hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> although the ſame was diſtant three daies of, and the<note n="b" place="margin">Exod ca
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; Deuter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ca. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> virgin not bound to go. <hi>Ieſus</hi> being then twelue yeares old, remained in
<hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> The virgin <hi>Marie</hi> not finding her child, the firſt daie at night, amongſt her kins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folkes, in whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie ſhe thought that he had gone (for as<note n="c" place="margin">In cap Lucae Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſ. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Mar. li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>4.</hi> c.
<hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bede</hi> ſaith, it was a cuſtome among the Iewes, in their deuotions, to go ſeperate men from weomen, and that the children might go with whome of them they would) ſhe returned back with
<hi>Ioſeph</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:6438:28"/>to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> where the third daie ſhe founde him in the temple in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the Doctors. And his mother asking him what he meant to tarie in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> &amp; make him ſelfe be ſought with ſo much griefe, he aunſwered that they ought to remember, that he being ſent to ſeeke the glorie of his father, was to be found in the affaires and place of his father.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>template how the virgin went yearelie, for her deuotion, at the feaſt of <hi>Paſche</hi> to adore in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and once it fel out that ſhe turning backe, <hi>Ieſus</hi> remained there.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Contemplate how the virgin <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> not ſeeing her beloued <hi>Ieſus</hi> at night, nor finding him amongſt her friends and kinsfolke, with whome ſhe thought he had bene, ful of ſorow ſhe went out of hand with <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> to ſeeke him in
<hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 Conſider how the afflicted mother after three daies weeping &amp; ſuſpiring, found her beloued ſonne in the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6438:28"/>amongſt the Doctors, whoſe ſight and preſence gaue her no leſſe ioye, then his abſence and loſſe had giuen her ſorowe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Learne of the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> not to abandon nor blame thy deuotions, when for them thou doſt ſuffer anie aduerſitie or dammage.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Learne alſo not to delaie to ſeeke Chriſt, and haue him with thee, for beſides that thou doſt loſe much, thou doſt put thy ſelfe in great daunger.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thou ſeeſt that the virgin did not find Chriſt amongſt her kinsfolke, but in the Temple, ſo likewiſe thou ſhalt find him in ſpiritual things, but not in fleaſh and bloud.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>OF THE VIRGIN Maries ſpouſe Joſeph his death. 14.</head>
               <p>IT is not altogeather certaine at what time the virgin
<hi>Marie</hi> became
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6438:29"/>a widowe.<note n="a" place="margin">Haereſ.
<hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>8</hi> contra Antid.</note> 
                  <hi>Epiphanius</hi> is of opinion that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> deceaſed, <hi>Chriſt</hi> being thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tene years old.<note n="b" place="margin">In com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>end. hiſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Cedrenus</hi> ſaith he died whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> was of thirtie years.<note n="c" place="margin">Ambro. de inſtit.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>irg. c <hi>7.</hi> &amp; epiſt. <hi>79.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> and<note n="d" place="margin">Hiero. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uid.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Hierome</hi> do write onlie, that
<hi>Ioſeph</hi> was then dead, when <hi>Chriſt</hi> was crucified.<note n="e" place="margin">Matth. ca. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> This holie man was of the roial ſtocke of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and being choſen of God for the cuſtodie of two ſo pretious treaſures, as were <hi>Christ</hi> &amp; the
<hi>Virgin,</hi> it is to be thought that he was ſuch a one, as the holie ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and<note n="f" place="margin">Damaſce de fide or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thad lib.
<hi>4.</hi> ca. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> auncient fathers do report him to haue bene, <hi>iuſt, religious, prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, faithful,</hi> and indued with manie other vertues. He was not onlie <hi>chaſte,</hi> as<note n="g" place="margin">Hiero. cont. Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Hierome,</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Augu. Serm. <hi>15.</hi> de nat. Do mini.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> and others do affirme, but alſo did die a virgin, as not hauing anie other wife then the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> with whome, as<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> p. q. <hi>28.</hi> ar <hi>4.</hi> &amp; ad Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat. ca. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>S. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> ſaith he vowed virginitie. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the virgin was a moſt beautiful creature, neuertheles her countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce did caſt forth ſuch holines and grace, that as<note n="k" place="margin">Lib<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>1.</hi> reuel c. 1 &amp; lib. <hi>3</hi> ca.
<hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>S. Briget</hi> writeth ſhe moued al that did behold her to the loue of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6438:29"/>and much more did ſhe moue
<hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> to the ſame, whoſe concupiſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſaith<note n="l" place="margin">De nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Mar. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>3.</hi> Caniſ. lib. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Gerſon,</hi> was ether extinguiſhed or ſo repreſſed, that he neuer fealt in him ſelfe anie diſordinate motion.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Contemplate how the holie old man <hi>Ioſeph</hi> being neare the end of his life, <hi>Ieſus</hi> and the virgin did help him to die wel, whoſe ſoule was forthwith caried by the Angel into <hi>Abrahams boſome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 Contemplate how the virgin, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming her ſelfe to gods wil, did ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte with patience the death of her faithful ſpouſe, albeit the ſame was to her a thing verie incommodious, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the life of ſuch a ſainct did much help and comfort her.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plate how the virgin, though ſhe remained young and needie, did not therfore lament of god, nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of her ſtate, nor enuie at thoſe that were maried, but ſeeke by good woorkes to pleaſe god alſo in that ſtate of widowhead, and to perfect
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6438:30"/>her ſelfe in the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Be thou pure and chaſte as <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and affected to the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> and ſhe wil aide thee in that daungerous paſſage of death.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 If in the aduerſities that God doth ſend thee, thou be impatient &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, thou doeſt loſe the fruit thereof, &amp; tribulations become more greuous.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Learne of the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> to pleaſe god, and according to his wil, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect thy ſelfe in the ſtate he hath put thee.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>OF THE VIRGIN Marie in time of her vvidow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head. 15.</head>
               <p>THrough the death of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> there grewe to the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> ſome difficultie of houſehould,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> cem ca.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; <hi>9.</hi> &amp; lib. <hi>3.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.
<hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> yet <hi>a Sabel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licus</hi> writeth that ſhe had ſo wel diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her ſpiritual exerciſes, and the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of her houſe, that the one did
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6438:30"/>not hinder the other. For ſhe did giue the beginning of the daie to godlie contemplations, and that towards night ſhe did applie to read holie ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of which ſhe was ſo greatlie ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moured, that, as<note n="b" place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> de virgini.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> writeth ſhe repeated ſleeping the night, what the daie time ſhe had reade. She had her appointed time for ſleepe, albeit as<note n="c" place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> reuel. ca.
<hi>10.</hi> &amp; lib. <hi>3.</hi> ca. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>S. Briget</hi> reporteth, ſhe had ſo accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed her bodie, that not onlie in ſleepe, but in whatſoeuer els it was obedient to the ſoule.<note n="d" place="margin">de arcan Catho. ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. lib. <hi>7.</hi> ca. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Galatinus</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs that the virgin had ſuch a ſpirit of propheſie, that ſhe did ſtil ſhut her eyes and eares, when ſhe was to ſee, or heare anie things vnlawful or imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent.<note n="e" place="margin">In epist. Caniſ. lib. <hi>1.</hi> ca. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Ignatius</hi> doth likewiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, that the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> was ſo ſound in the loue of her neighbour, that ſhe did not onlie ſhew her ſelfe kinde to the Iewes, that perſecuted Chriſt, but hauing compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their imperfections, did alſo ſeeke to do them al kind of ſeruice, that ſhe could. when <hi>Chriſt</hi> did come to her houſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6438:31"/>with his Apoſtles, ſhe did feele parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ioye of ſpirit, ſo that ſhe receaued them with great chearfulnes &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Conſider how the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> now a widowe, was no leſſe diligent in prayer, then in the care of her houſe ſo that when <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles did come to her, ſhe cauſed al things to be in readines according to her po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Conſider how the virgin in her conuerſation was ſo graue and modeſt that ſhe was amiable to al, and with her ex<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>aple did inflame others to loue God and vertue.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Contemplate how the virgin did neuer murmour, nor permit others in her preſence to ſpeake euil of the Iewes, that were her ſonnes enimies, but did excuſe them and praye god for them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Haſt thou a deſire, that thy tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral affaires maie haue good ſucceſſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6438:31"/>do thy ſpiritual exerciſes wel, as the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> did hers.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Thou ſhalt neuer inflame others to vertue, if thou be cold in prayer, and careleſſe in giuing good example.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 To excuſe, &amp; praye god for him that doth perſecute thee, is the reu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of good Chriſtians: grateful to god, diſpleaſing the diuel, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to the ſoule.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>OF CHRIST HIS departing from the virgin Marie. 16.</head>
               <p>CHriſt our Sauiour was in a towne called
<hi>Bethania,</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Ianſeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corc.
<hi>128.</hi> &amp; Stella. in Luc.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> two miles of <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> in the houſe of <hi>Martha</hi> &amp;
<hi>Marie Magdalen,</hi> as<note n="b" place="margin">Bonau. in medie. c.
<hi>4.</hi> &amp; <hi>62.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bonauenture</hi> ſaith, with whome alſo the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> was, and when vppon thurſdaie he had ſent
<hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> to Ieruſalem, to find a place where to celebrate the <hi>Paſche,</hi> the time of his departure now come, he tooke his leaue of his deare mother
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6438:32"/>which remained fraught with ſorow, becauſe ſhe knew that <hi>Ieſus</hi> was to be deliuered vp into his enimies hands, to endure exceeding torments, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallie to die vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe as a thiefe. There is no doubt but that the virgin weeping and taking no repoſe al that night, did expect ſtil to heare moſt heauie newes of her ſonne.<note n="c" place="margin">Caniſ. lib <hi>4.</hi> ca. 25.</note> And in deede as ſoone as <hi>Ieſus</hi> was apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the garden, a meſſenger, who peraduenture was ſome one of the Apoſtles, went to <hi>Bethania</hi> to carie ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings to the virgin, how <hi>Ieſus</hi> was now betrayed by <hi>Iudas,</hi> taken by the Iewes, and leade awaie bound to the Iudges. The virgin <hi>Marie</hi> hauing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode this doleful newes, ſobbing and ſighing, and accompanied with the other <hi>Maries,</hi> went to Ieruſalem.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>template how the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> when ſhe vnderſtoode of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> that now the hower of his paſſion was come; and that for this effect he was to go to Ieruſalem, it being his eternal
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6438:32"/>fathers wil, was ſtrooken at the hart with ſuch bitter ſorowe, that not able to ſpeake, ſhe did power out from her eyes ſtreames of teares.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>template how the virgin, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſhe ſtoode lamenting, had newes that <hi>Ieſus</hi> was then taken. Think now what a cruel dart this was to the hart of that moſt louing and kind mother, which did beare ſo great affection to her ſonne <hi>Ieſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>template how the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> ſtraight vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this newes went to wards Ieruſalem, offering her ſelfe, if it had ſo pleaſed almightie god, ether to die for <hi>Ieſus,</hi> or to die with
<hi>Ieſus:</hi> ſeeing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat to liue without <hi>Ieſus,</hi> was to her
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> continual and moſt painful death.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 If the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> did remaine ſo
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uch afflicted for the departing of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hriſt,</hi> in what ſtate ſhal that miſerable
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ule be, which
<hi>Chriſt</hi> hath abandon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by reaſon of ſinne?</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Learne of the virgin not to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heme god, nor be angrie, when anie
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6438:33"/>il news is told thee.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 If to liue without <hi>Ieſus</hi> be a moſt painful death, what ſhal it be to liue in mortal ſinne, which is to liue againſt <hi>Ieſus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>OF THE <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IRGIN Maries going to mount Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarie
<hi>17.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVhen the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> entred into
<hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Bonau. in Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio.</note> ſhe did finde the whole cittie bent and moued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Ieſus;</hi> and becauſe the people were incited, encouraged and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by the Scribes and Phariſes, to cauſe <hi>Christ</hi> to be condemned as a malefactor, the afflicted mother was conſtrained to heare infinite iniuries, and horrible blaſphemies againſt her ſonne <hi>Ieſus,</hi> throughout al the ſtreetes of Ieruſalem, by which ſhe was to paſſe going to mount <hi>Caluarie.</hi> But how much this virgin did ſuffer this daie, which was good fridaie: holie
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:6438:33"/>fathers do declare with diuers exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples.<note n="b" place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> de fid. or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. ca. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Damaſcene</hi> writeth that the virgin <hi>marie</hi> did feele thoſe bitter pangs, and paines at the time of <hi>Chriſt</hi> his paſſion, which ſhe did not feele in the time of his natiuitie. And<note n="c" place="margin">In tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctat de Compas. virginis.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Bernard</hi> ſaith, that what effect the nailes, and other inſtruments (of torment) did woorke in the bodie of our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt;</hi> the verie ſame they wrought in the ſoule of the virgin, by reaſon of her mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie compaſſion.<note n="d" place="margin">Luthim. in Luc. ca. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Luthimius</hi> and<note n="e" place="margin">Beda ib. &amp; Caniſ. lib.
<hi>4.</hi> ca. <hi>25.</hi> &amp; <hi>26.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bede</hi> doe record, that the paine of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours paſſion, did pearce euen through the harte of the virgin, like that ſharpe ſword, that was prophecied &amp; foretold by holie <hi>Simeon:</hi> in ſomuch that<note n="f" place="margin">Anſel. lib de ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellen. B. Mariae. ca. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Anſelmus,</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Bernard ſerm ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num mag.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Bernad</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ldeph. Ser. <hi>2.</hi> de aſsum. vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gini.</note> 
                  <hi>Ildepho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſus</hi> and others doe affirme, that the virgin
<hi>Marie</hi> was a martyre, and more then a martyre.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Contemplate how the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> made that voiage, weeping al the waie: and arriued that ſhe was at
<hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> ſhe did vnderſtand the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6438:34"/>and outrages done to her ſonne, which were ſo manie ſwords to her harte.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Contemplate how it alſo pearced her harte, to heare reported, that not onlie anie one perſon had not ſpoken ought in fauour of the innocent <hi>Ieſus,</hi> he hauing beſtowed ſo manie benifits vpon them al: but alſo that he was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken of his owne diſciples.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plate moreouer, what paine that of the virgin was, when going to mount Caluarie, ſhe did heare the ſtrokes of thoſe wicked torturers, that ſo cruellie nailed her ſonne to the Croſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Learne of the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> how thou muſt behaue thy ſelfe in tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: firſt thou muſt not grudge againſt the creatures, that do thee anie harme or iniure, no more then the virgin did againſt thoſe, that ether did procure the death of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or execute the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Thou muſt not lament nether of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:6438:34"/>thine owne condition, nor of God who did permit it to be ſuch as it is, but ſeeke to take profit thereby for thy ſoule, as god doth pretend.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Albeit thou feele griefe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt, yet with thy wil and higher part of the ſoule, which remaineth free, thou muſt praiſe god.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>OF THE VIRGIN Marie ſeing Chriſt on the Croſſe. 18.</head>
               <p>THe virgin <hi>Marie</hi> when ſhe was come vp to mount Caluarie,<note n="a" place="margin">Ioan. ca. <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> did ſee her ſonne crucified betwixt two thieues: and whiles with moſt dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful teares ſhe ſtoode beholding this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable pageant, <hi>Ieſus</hi> did regard her from the croſſe with great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, &amp; ſhewing her
<hi>Iohn</hi> his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſaid to her, <hi>vvoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> behold thy ſonne,</hi> and after he ſaid to the diſciple, <hi>Behold thy mother.</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Serm. stabatiux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Cruc.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Anſelmus</hi> doth auou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, that the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> ſhewed in that place ſuch rare vertues, as ſhe was
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:6438:35"/>the glorie of al weomen ſex: for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the diſciples had forſaken their mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, the virgin did not abandone him, and when others fled for feare, ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained ſtedfaſt in faith, and conſtant at the foote of the Croſſe: with greate ſorow ſhe had exceeding patience: ſhe did not curſe, nor murmour, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund reuenge againſt her enemies at gods hand. And<note n="c" place="margin">In ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem. Ser. Stabat.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Bernard</hi> ſaith, that the virgin, although ſhe was ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with ſorowe, did not yet commit anie vndecent act, nor ſhew anie ſigne of impatie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but keepe her ſelfe alwayes within the bounds of reaſon and modeſtie.<note n="d" place="margin">In la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Caniſ lib.
<hi>4.</hi> ca. <hi>25.</hi> &amp; <hi>26.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>S. Ephrem</hi> the deacon doth alſo write, that the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, at the foote of the Croſſe, did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore, and worſhippe with al reuerence the woundes, the afflictions, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnanimitie of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> &amp; eftſons offer them vp to god, for the redemption of mankind.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Contemplate the exceeding great ſorow and compaſſion of the virgin
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:6438:35"/>
                     <hi>Marie,</hi> when ſhe did ſee her innocent and deerelie beloued ſonne al beraied with bloud, &amp; as a malefactour han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging vpon the Croſſe, betwixt two thieues.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Conſider how the virgin was ſo afflicted, that
<hi>Ieſus</hi> enduring the cruel torment of the croſſe, had compaſſion of her, and therfore gaue her <hi>S. Iohn</hi> for her ſonne, and her ſelfe for his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Contemplate how the virgin, at the death of her beloued ſonne was the moſt diſcomforted of al mothers, for that ſhe was preſent, and yet could not help him, who died in ſo greate paines and torments.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Euerie time that thou doeſt looke vpon the Crucifixe, thinke that for thy ſinnes the ſonne god was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and ſo with the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> thou wilt haue compaſſion and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe of him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 In al thy neceſſities make recourſe to the virgin, ſeeing god hath giuen
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6438:36"/>vs her for our mother, in the perſon of
<hi>S. Iohn,</hi> and vs to her for her children.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 If <hi>Christ</hi> and the virgin did ſuffer in this life ſo great afflictions, how doſt thou thinke to liue without aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and in continual pleaſure &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>OF THE VIRGIN Marie houlding Chriſt dead in her armes. 19.</head>
               <p>THe virgin <hi>Marie</hi> ſtoode at the foote of the Croſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Matth. a. <hi>27.</hi> Mar. ca.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5. Luc.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a. <hi>23.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oan. ca. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>9.</hi>
                  </note> when at
<hi>Ieſus</hi> death the ſunne was darkened, and the earth did quake: and being verie deſirous to haue in her armes the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of her beloued ſonne, behould, one of the ſouldiars with a ſpeare ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his ſide. There is no doubte but that this ſpeare did wound alſo the bleſſed mother with exceeding griefe, who although ſhe were diſpleaſed with that fiercenes of the ſouldiar, which did ſhew him ſelfe ſo cruelle to wards one that was deade, yet ſhe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:6438:36"/>was not moued againſt him.<note n="b" place="margin">Caniſ. lrb. <hi>4.</hi> de B. Mariae. ca.
<hi>26.</hi>
                  </note> To be ſhorte, vpon fridaie at night, becauſe it was not expedient that the deade bodies ſhould remaine vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Croſſe in the
<hi>Sabboth,</hi> the bodie of <hi>Ieſus</hi> was vnnailed, and taken downe from the Croſſe and laid in the armes of his pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful mother, which ſhe moſt dearelie did embrace and worſhip, and often kiſſe thoſe holie wounds, offering them vp to the eternal father for the ſaluation of the world. Here the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Maries did weepe moſt abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, ſeeking by this meanes to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie the virgin, whoſe ſorowe and lamentation, as<note n="c" place="margin">In Ioan. ca <hi>19</hi> Serm Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xta Crucem.</note> 
                  <hi>Anſelmus</hi> ſaith, was paſſing greate, becauſe the loue that ſhe did beare to
<hi>Ieſus,</hi> was alſo greate: yet the ſame was alwaies ioined with ſuch comlines and graue behaueour, that no man could reprehend it.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>template how the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe could not haue her ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne aliue, deſired to haue him being dead: but before ſhe could obtaine this, a ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diar
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:6438:37"/>with a ſpeare did open his ſide, not without horrour &amp; griefe of the mother.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Contemplate the dolorous la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation that the virgin made, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe had once in her armes that ſacred bodie whoſe wounds ſhe did kiſſe with great deuotion, and waſh them with ſtreames of teares.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thinke what griefe of harte the virgin did feele, when ſhe was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to leaue that holie treaſure to be buried, and afterwards was forced to depart from the ſepulchre, which yet ſhe did not without manie ſobbes and ſighes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Learne of the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> how thou muſt behaue thy ſelfe, in the death of thy deare friends. Thinke firſt that god being a moſt kind father, what he doeth and permitteth, he doth for our good.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Hence it is that thou muſt not la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nether of god, nor of his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, nor of thine owne caſe.</p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:6438:37"/>
                  <p n="3">3 Suffer not thy ſelfe ſo to be caried awaye with ſorowe, although the ſame be verie great, that thou commit therby anie lightnes or vndecencie: hauing ſtil before thine eyes, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie and grauitie of the virgin <hi>Marie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>OF THE <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IRGIN Marie ſeeing Chriſt reſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citate. 20.</head>
               <p>THere is noe certaintie, into what place the virgin
<hi>Marie</hi> did retire her ſelfe, after that <hi>Ieſus</hi> was buried, nor in what place <hi>Chriſt</hi> did appeare vnto her after his reſurrection: if not, that<note n="a" place="margin">Lib <hi>2.</hi> hiſto. ca. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Nicephorus</hi> doth ſaye, that ſhe dwelt in <hi>S. Iohns</hi> houſe, neere to <hi>Sion</hi> in <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> And this is verie likelie to be ſoe, for that the virgin was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme weake, partelie in reſpect of her continual weeping, partelie alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe al that daie ſhe had eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothing: in ſo much that it is credible ſhe went not from Ieruſalem, but that <hi>S. Iohn,</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:6438:38"/>to whome <hi>Chriſt</hi> commended her a little before, did leade her to his houſe, where ſhe expected her ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne knowing for certaine, that he was to riſe from death the third daie. But be it how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, that which<note n="b" place="margin">Auguſ lib. de ſancta vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginitate. ca <hi>3.</hi> Ruper. lib. <hi>7.</hi> diu. offic. ca.
<hi>25.</hi> Anſelm. de excel. virg. ca. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> holie fathers doe affirme, &amp; is certaine, is this: that the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> was the firſt, to whome oure Sauiour appeared after his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And as<note n="c" place="margin">Epiph. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on. haer. &amp; libel. Aetiq Caniſ. lib. <hi>5.</hi> ca.
<hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Epiphanius</hi> doth write, ſhe was the firſt that did adore him, being glorious. In deede it was conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for ſuch a ſonne, ſo to behaue him ſelfe towards ſuch a mother, not onlie becauſe he gaue vs the lawe to honour father &amp; mother, but alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the virgin did receaue extreme paine and ſorowe, of his paſſion and death, more then anie othres, yea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue al others: ſoe that ſhe deſerued to be comforted before anie other, &amp; more then anie els whoſoeuer.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>template how the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> being as it were buried in her cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber for ſorowe, <hi>Ieſus</hi> appeared vnto
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:6438:38"/>her raiſed from death, and being al glorious, al brighte, and accompained with ſquadrons of Angels, and holie fathers out of Limbo: &amp; thinke what vnſpeakeable ioie the virgin did feele of ſo glorious apparition.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>template how the virgin, ſeeing <hi>Ieſus</hi> ſo glorious, did firſt worſhip him as her God, and then embrace him as her ſonne, kiſſing eftſons the ſacred woundes, which did ſhine in his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious body as ſo many pretious ſtones.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Contemplate how the virgin did giue her ſonne moſt hartie thankes, for his deare viſiting of her: and praie him to goe comfort the Apoſtles and other deuout perſons, with his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous reſurrection.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 If thou wilt endure nothing for the loue of
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> thou ſhalt not be vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited nor comforted of him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Learne of the virgin not to be to ioyful in time of proſperitie, but to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore and thanke God the author of al good.</p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:6438:39"/>
                  <p n="3">3 Learne alſo of her to haue charitie towards thy neighbours, and to wiſh and procure theire comfort, in time of afflictions and trauails.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>OF THE VIRGIN Marie after Chriſt his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion. 21.</head>
               <p>AS the common opinion is, the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Marie</hi> liued fifteene yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Aſcenſion of <hi>Chriſt</hi> into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: in which time ſhe was occupied in aduauncing the primitiue church of
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> which in thoſe beginnings was mightilie perſecuted; ſo that ſhe did animate al, &amp; teache them how to behaue them ſelues in their actions &amp; perſecutions, moreouer<note n="a" place="margin">De ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel Mar. ca. <hi>7.</hi> &amp; Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrat in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rat de dor mit Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parae.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Anſelmus</hi> doth write that the virgin vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding more profoundlie thoſe verities, which the holie Ghoſt had reuealed, did teach and declare manie things alſo to the Apoſtles, with whome ſhe alwaies liued familiarlie, leading with them an Apoſtolical life.<note n="b" place="margin">Tragae. de Chriſte patiente.</note>
                  <hi>Nazianze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:6438:39"/>ſaith, that after the Aſcenſion of
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſhe did foretel the Iewes of the deſtruction of
<hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> for the ſinne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted againſt the
<hi>Meſsias.</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Serm. de Aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione.</note>
                  <hi>Sophro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> alſo doth report, that oftentimes ſhe viſited the mount Caluarie, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſepulchre, and with great deuotion did kiſſe the footſteps of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which he le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t printed in the mounte Oliuet.<note n="d" place="margin">Caniſius lib. 5 ca. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> Some be of opinion that ſhe did liue of the common almes, with which the widowes of the primitiue Church were wont to be maintained.<note n="e" place="margin">Lib. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel. cit.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get</hi> writeth, that the virgin did not onlie fortifie and confirme thoſe new Chriſtians in their faith, but alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert manie Iewes and Gentiles to the knowledge of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and that for this cauſe, God did conſerue her aliue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Chriſt</hi> his Aſcenſion.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>template how after the Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as a miſtreſſe and giude of the faithful, wherfore in al theire doubts and trauails, they had recourſe to her.</p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:6438:40"/>
                  <p n="2">2 Contemplate how the virgin did receaue euerie one verie kindlie, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the afflicted, pacifie thoſe that were at diſcord, and inſtruct them al in the lawe &amp; faith of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in which good woorkes ſhe could not but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure manie incommodities.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Contemplate how the virgin at her times appointed, did giue her ſelf alſo to the conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plation of celeſtial things, and to viſit the holy places, leauing in al her actions rare examples of vertue, and excellent perfection.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 For ſo much as the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> was left vs for our miſtreſſe and guide; thou art vnwiſe, if thou goe not after her, folowing her vertues.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 If <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his mother did ſuffer manie incommodities, to help their neighbours, it is a ſigne, that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wil help others, muſt alſo endure ſome diſcommodite, and not ſeeke his owne contentment.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 If thou wilt haue affection to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie thinges, thinke vppon, them
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:6438:40"/>often, as the virgin did, and conſider that god did create and make thee for them, and not for theſe things vppon the earth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>OF THE VIRGIN Marie requeſting fauour to die. 22.</head>
               <p>VVHen the primitiue church, through the labours of the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
<hi>Marie,</hi> was for the ſpace of fifteene yeares meetelie wel eſtabliſhed, and encreaſed by perſecutions; the virgin demaunded of our Lord to end her Pilgrimage, and paſſe to an other life, there to be more vnited with her ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne. And the time being now come, which God had appointed for this purpoſe,<note n="a" place="margin">Lib <hi>2.</hi> hiſt ca.
<hi>21.</hi> Metaphras in orat de vita &amp; morte virgi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nis. Caniſ. lib
<hi>5.</hi> ca. <hi>2.</hi> &amp;. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Nicephorus</hi> doth report that our Lord ſent her an Angel, which brought her the ioiful newes of her departure from this baniſhement to heauen, and giuing her a braunche of a palme tree, foretold her the daie of her deceaſe. This tidings was to the virgin <hi>Marie</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:6438:41"/>of exceeding
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oie, and ſo deare, that ſhe could not be ſatiated to thanke God, but al ful of ioie, ſhe did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to her frinds and deuoute perſons the reuelation which ſhe had receaued from the Angel, and ſhewed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the braunche of palme which the ſame Angel brought her. She cauſed certaine poore garments that ſhe had, to be giuen to two poore widowes her neighbours <hi>Nichephorus</hi> doth more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer adde, that to the houſe where ſhe was, there came a greate multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Chriſtians, which with teares did lament, ſeeing them ſelues to be ſhortlie bereft of ſuch a miſtreſſe, and the onlie comfort that they had; but the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> did exhort them ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be glad, then to mourne and lament.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Conſider how the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> was inflamed with the loue of her ſonne <hi>Ieſus,</hi> in ſomuch that ſhe often demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of our Lord, to depart out of this life, to goe to him, and enioie
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:6438:41"/>him in heauen, remitting her ſelfe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles to his holie wil &amp; pleaſure.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Contemplate how the Angel ſent by God, did reueale to the virgin, that now was the time, in which ſhe muſt paſſe to a better life, to enioie euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinglie her dearelie beloued ſonne, and the fruite of her woorkes.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Contemplate the greate iubilie, which the virgin did feele of ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie newes: forſomuch as in this pilgri mage ſhe did nether deſire, nor thinke vppon anie other thing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Becauſe thou knoweſt not what is beſt for thee, thou muſt euen in thoſe things that ſeeme verie holie &amp; good, reſigne thy ſelf as the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> did, to the good pleaſure of almightie god.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 God is woont to graunt his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours at the time by him appointed, and therfore lament not, if thou doe not ſodenlie obtaine what thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeſt.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 If thou deſire that the tidings of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:6438:42"/>death be ioiful to thee, with draw thy thoughts from earth lie things, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect thy ſelfe to heauenlie things.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>OF THE VIRGIN Marie being neere to die. 23</head>
               <p>THe time approaching neere in which the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> was to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of his life to the celeſtial <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> God did not ceaſe to ſhew her new fauours, for he would that al the Apoſtles ſhould find them ſelues pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at her death as<note n="a" place="margin">Metaph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras orat de uita &amp; morib. B. virg Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pho lib.
<hi>2.</hi> hiſt. ca. <hi>3.</hi> Damaſce. orat. de. dormit &amp; aſſum virg.</note> manie writers do affirme. And ſetting a part the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of<note n="b" place="margin">Dion. Areop. de dui nomi. ca. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Dionyſius Areopagita,</hi> who was there preſent, I wil heere laye downe that, which.<note n="c" place="margin">Inuena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis apua Euthim in vet. hiſt.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Iuuenalis</hi> Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Ieruſalem did aunſwere to <hi>Marcianus</hi> Emperour being demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of him touching the death of the virgin <hi>Marie.</hi> Albeit, ſaith he, holy ſcripture doth not ſpeake of the death of the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> yet we haue by an auncient and moſt true tradition, that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:6438:42"/>at the time of her glorious parting out of this life, the Apoſtles that were in diuers parts of the world, in a moment were lifted vp into the aire, and came togeather in Ieruſalem, and were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the death of the virgin <hi>Marie.</hi> Beſides this
<hi>S.</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Anſel. de excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia virg. ca
<hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Anſelmus</hi> and<note n="e" place="margin">Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pho citat. ca. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus</hi> doe ſaie, that
<hi>Chriſt</hi> alſo came from heauen in companie of manie Angels, to be preſent him ſelfe in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at the death of his moſt deare mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to receaue her ſoule. The like long before theſe men did write<note n="f" place="margin">Vbi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra Caniſ. lib. <hi>5.</hi> ca.
<hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Damaſcenus,</hi> ſetting downe the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and ſpeeche, which paſt at that time betwixt the mother &amp; the ſonne, as heereafter ſhal be declared.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Contemplate how as ſoone as the time of the virgin
<hi>Maries</hi> happie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture was come, the Apoſtles came to Ieruſalem from diuers parts of the world to be there then preſent: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God diſpoſing this ſoe for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and comfort of the virgin.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Conſider how <hi>Chriſt</hi> oure Sauiour
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:6438:43"/>came alſo downe from heauen, to be preſent likewiſe him ſelfe at the death of his deare mother, and to receaue her ſoule.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Contemplate how the virgin, the more greater ioie ſhe felt in her heart, did the more humble her ſelfe, and with moſt cordial affection thanke our Lord, for ſo manie greate graces and fauours.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 In the time of thie death or ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, procure to haue alwaies ſome ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual parſons neere vnto thee.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Ceaſe not to leade a vertuous life as the virgin
<hi>Marie</hi> did, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> wil not faile to aſſiſt thee at thie death.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Giue thie ſelfe to God with al thie heart, and ſerue him with true humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, if thou deſire to liue and die con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:6438:43"/>
               <head>OF THE <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IRGIN Maries death. 24.</head>
               <p>THe virgin <hi>Marie</hi> deceaſed in Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem in <hi>S. Iohns</hi> houſe, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout threeſcore and three years old.<note n="a" place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> reu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>la. ca. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>S. Brigett</hi> telleth vs that ſhe died moſt quietlie, without anie feare or paine.<note n="b" place="margin">In orat. de aſſump Deipare.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Damaſcenus</hi> is of opinion, that a litle before the virgin gaue vp her ghoſt, ſhe ſaid to
<hi>Ieſus,</hi> Into thy hands o my ſonne, I commend my ſpirite: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue now my ſowle ſo deare vnto thee, which thou haſt kept free from al ſpot of ſinne. To thee likewiſe and not to the earth doe I giue my body, in which it pleaſed thee to dwel. drawe me to thee, that I maie be there, where thou art, the bleſſed fruite of my wombe. The ſelf ſame father doth alſo ſaie, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> did aunſwere her in this ſort-come, o my bleſſed mother into my repoſe, come o pure &amp; beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful amongſt al weomen, becauſe in
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:6438:44"/>thee there is no ſpotte.<note n="c" place="margin">Lib. <hi>2</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hiſt. ca. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Nicephorus</hi> doth recount that the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> ſpeaking theſe words, <hi>Be it done to me againe according to thine vvorde,</hi> gaue vp her bleſſed ſowle into the deare hands of her ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne <hi>Ieſus,</hi> &amp; ſo ſhe remained as if ſhe had be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſleepe<note n="d" place="margin">In hiſt.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ete. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Iuuenalis</hi> alſo did ſay to the Emperour <hi>Marcianus,</hi> that at the death of the virgin were ſeene manie Angels, and moſt ſweete ſongs of the highe powers, and the virgin in an vnſpeakeable manner did giue vp her gracious ſoule into the hands of God, moreouer<note n="e" place="margin">In orat. le Aſſum to. Caniſ.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ib. <hi>5.</hi> ca.</note>
                  <hi>Andreas</hi> Biſſhop of <hi>Candie</hi> doth tel how there came a greate multitude of Angels from heauen at the death of the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>template how the virgin being readie to paſſe out of this life, hauing commended her ſoule to her maker, did alſo commend to the Apoſtles the faithful of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> particularlie thoſe that were afflicted and troubled.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 After this done, lifting vp her eyes
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:6438:44"/>to heauen, and beholding ſtedfaſtlie her ſonne <hi>Ieſus,</hi> ſhe demaunded his benediction; which obtained, that moſt bleſſed ſoule of hers, did depart out of the bodie without anie feare, and did flie into the armes of <hi>Ieſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 Contemplate how <hi>Ieſus</hi> did rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aue the moſt pure ſoule of his dearlie beloued mother, and with Angelical hymnes did conuaie the ſame into heauen; thoſe that were then preſent remaining aſtonied, and with teares giuing thanks &amp; praiſe to God for al.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 See what account the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> did make of helping her neighbours; that departing out of this world ſhe did commend them to the Apoſtles.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 If thow wilt not be afraid at thy death time; procure that thie conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence be cleane from ſinne.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thou art fullie deceaued, if being a liue thou care not for heauen; and yet doſt thinke, that dying thie ſoule ſhal flie thither.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:6438:45"/>
               <head>OF THE VIRGIN Maries funerals and burial. 25.</head>
               <p>AFter that the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> was departed this life, the Apoſtles tooke her ſacred body out of the bed, in which before her death ſhe did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine appareled and put in moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent maner, and laide her vppon the biere.<note n="a" place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> biſt. ca.
<hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Nicephorus</hi> doth report that there was great concourſe of deafe, blinde, and other lame folks, who al were moſt miraculouſlie cured with touching onlie that ſacred bodie. This done-there was a proceſſion ſet in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre: &amp; ſome of the Apoſtles we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t before with lights in theire hands, ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers caried the coffin, and al ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing holie himmes<note n="b" place="margin">Andreas Crete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. orat de Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſump. B. Virginus. Damaſcin orat de Dormit. &amp; Aſſáp virg. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſ. lib. <hi>5.</hi> ca. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> went towards getſſemani, where ſhe before had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be buried. The ſame au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor doth recount, and others alſo do avouche, that through al the waie were ſeene in the aire manie ſquadro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:6438:45"/>of Angels, which did accompanie the bleſſed bodie of theire Queene. He ſaith moreouer, that a certaine prieſt of the Iewes, moued of haterd and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, was ſo raſh and vnconſiderate, as to puſh the beire thinking to throw the ſame to the grounde: but he was foorth with puniſhed by god, for that his hands were ſeparated from his armes, and did ſticke hanging to the coffin. whereuppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the poore wretche aſtonied with the miracle, did ſoden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie repent him ſelfe, and with teares demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded pardon: ſo that by <hi>S. Peters</hi> appointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the proceſſion was ſtaied, and the Iew approching neere to the coffin with great reuerence, his hands by a new miracle were reſtored to him againe.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Contemplate how as ſoone as the virgin
<hi>Marie</hi> was dead, the Apoſtles with great reuerence, but not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out teares, did put her bodie in ordre to carie it to be buried, and to do the funeral exequies accuſtomed.</p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:6438:46"/>
                  <p n="2">2 Moreouer conſider the proceſſion, with which that holie tabernacle of god, was caried to be buried by the Apoſtles: accompanied with a great multitude of Chriſtians, which by the waie did ſtil ſinge holie himmes.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plate how when they were come to the place, and had celebrated the exequies that ſacred and virgin bodie was of al bleſſed with great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence and deuotion, and after ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourablie buried.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Learne heerehence how to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate funeralls after a chriſtian man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. firſt thou muſt not put thie ſelf to ſuperfluous charges in things, which do not helpe the ſoule of him that is dead, but rather nouriſh vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in thoſe that be aliue.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Thou muſt not lament the dead immoderatlie, but rather praie for their ſowles.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thou muſt make account of fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rales, as of a warning which god doth giue thee, therby to prepare thy ſelfe to die wel.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:6438:46"/>
               <head>OF THE VIRGIN Maries Aſſumption. 26.</head>
               <p>THat holy Biſſhop<note n="a" place="margin">Nicepho lib.
<hi>2.</hi> hiſt. ca. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>S. Iuuenalis</hi> doth tel vs, how the Apoſtles re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained at the ſepulchre of the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> for three daies, hearing conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuallie a moſt ſweete harmonie of holy himnes. After three daies were paſt, it ſeemed to the Apoſtles for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of <hi>S. Thomas</hi> (who was not preſent at her death) to open the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, and to ſhew him the ſacred body. And when they had diſcouered the place, they found not the body, but they did feele a moſt ſweete ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and found onlie the linnen in in which the body was wrapped, which they did kiſſe for deuotion. And that the bleſſed virgin was raiſed vp the third daie, and in ſoule &amp; body aſſumpted into heauen many holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doe tel vs.<note n="b" place="margin">Oratio. de Aſsup.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Damaſcenus</hi> doth write that the virgin as the daughter of the old <hi>Adam,</hi> was ſubiect to the old
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:6438:47"/>lawe of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>: but in as much as ſhe was the mother of the liuing god, ſhe was from the ſepulchre conioined to him.<note n="c" place="margin">In ento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio de dor nit virg.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Part. <hi>3.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nnal. &amp;
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d Alip.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Serm. de
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it. &amp; lormit.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>irg Caniſ
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ib. <hi>5.</hi> ca.
<hi>4.5.</hi> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
                  <hi>Andreas</hi> Biſſhop of <hi>Candia</hi> doth ſay in this ſort. She that brought forth the author of life, being raiſed vp againe, findeth her ſelfe now there where is preſent the perpetual foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of life.
<hi>Michael Glycas</hi> doth report that the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> died according to the lawes of nature, but by grace ſhe was raiſed againe, as her ſonne. <hi>Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrastes</hi> alſo doth auouche that the moſt bleſſed body of the virgin, was by god tranſlated into the diuine and celeſtial tabernacles.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Contemplate in what manner the bleſſed body of the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> laide in the ſepulchre, was not onlie voide of corruption, but alſo did caſt from it ſelfe a moſt ſweete ſauour.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Contemplate how God ordained that the third daie the ſoule of the bleſſed virgin <hi>Marie</hi> ſhould deſcend from heauen to earth, to be reunited
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:6438:47"/>to the bodie her faithful companion, of which ſhe receaued no ſmal ioie and contentment.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Contemplate how that glorious ſoule came from heauen accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with ſquadrons of Angels, and ſo was reunited to the bodie: in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the virgin being raiſed the third daie, went into heauen with greate triumph.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 If thou deſire that thie bodie giue a ſweete ſauour to God after thou art dead: endeauour to keepe it chaſt whileſt thou art aliue.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 If thou procure that thie bodie be a dwelling place for god heere on earth, he wil honour and exalt it in heauen.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 If thou wilt mount vp to heauen triumpha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as oure Ladie did, be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble heere on earth and ſuffer not thie ſelf to be ouercome of thie paſſions.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:6438:48"/>
               <head>OF THE VIRGIN Maries entring into heauen. 27</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>EPiphanius</hi> doth plainlie confeſſe,<note place="margin">Sermo. le Laudi. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. virg.</note> that no tongue of men or Angels is ſufficient to expreſſe the glorie and triumph, that the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> had in heauen: and concluding he ſaith that next vnder god ſhe is Superiour to al.<note n="b" place="margin">Sermo.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. de aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>up. virg.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Bernard</hi> alſo writeth that none can thinke with what glorie the Queene of the world did enter into heauen; with what affect of deuotion the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial legions did behould her: with what cheerful countenance &amp; diuine embracings ſhe was receaued of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> and exalted aboue al other creatures.<note n="c" place="margin">Sermo. le aſſump.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urg.</note>
                  <hi>Sophronius</hi> doth tel in particular how in the Aſſumption of the virgin, thoſe celeſtial Citizens went to meete her with al ſolemnitie: and ſo enuironed with heauenlie brightnes, ſhe was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted by them with muſicke to the throne which was prepared for her:
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:6438:48"/>and how the feaſt of the Aſſumption, which we celebrate but once a yeare, is perpetual to al that heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lie Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, and to thoſe bleſſed ſpirites.<note n="d" place="margin">In eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. de ſanc. deipa.</note> 
                  <hi>Athanaſius</hi> doth ſet downe the praiſes which each Ierarchie did ſing to the virgin <hi>Marie.</hi> And<note n="e" place="margin">Lib. de excil virg. ca. <hi>8.</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſ lib.
<hi>5.</hi> ca. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Anſelmus</hi> doth ſaie moreouer that God exalted the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> his mother aboue al the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and placed her in a throne of glorie, making her the Soueraigne ouer al creatures. The like doe ſay al thoſe holie fathers that write of the virgin, or of her Aſſumption.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>template how the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> entring into heauen, the celeſtial coorte went to meete her, by which ſhe was receaued with vniuerſal ioie as the mother of god and Queene of heauen.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Contemplate how aſcending to the place prepared for her, before the creation of the world, aboue al the quiars of Angels, euery Ierarchie of thoſe bleſſed ſpirites did ſing theire
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:6438:49"/>praiſe to the moſt ſacred virgin.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>template how the virgin being placed in her ſeate next to the throne of the moſt bleſſed Trinitie, at the right hand of her ſonne, al the court of heauen did encline them ſelues, and doe reuerence to their Queene.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 If thou deſire to be receaued in heauen with honour, as the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> was, receaue <hi>Chriſt</hi> on earth with loue and humilitie.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 They ſhal be praiſed of the Angels in heauen, which haue eſchewed the praiſes of men vppon earth.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 The more that thou ſhalt a baſe thy ſelf in this life for the loue of god, the more thou ſhalt be exalted in heauen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>OF THE VIRGIN Maries protection in heauen of her deuoutes: 28.</head>
               <p>THe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tents of this laſt hiſtorie is ſo manifeſt and cleere, that we neede not quote anie other authors then our
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:6438:49"/>ſelues: forſomuch as we al doe ſee, that in euerie kingdome, in euerie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, and in euerie cittie though it be neuer ſo litle, there is to be found ſome image of our Ladie that doth worke miracles, &amp; to which deuoute perſons haue particular recourſe, to obtaine graces and fauours of God, by meanes of the virgin <hi>Marie.</hi> And this hath bene an ordinarie thing ſince the beginning of the primitiue Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Now who is he that wil ſay, that this is not to be aſcribed to the particular protection, which the virgin hath in heauen of her deuoutes heere on earth? who wil ſay, that ſhe is not fauoured of that infinite maine ſea of al good nes? ſeeing that ſhe doth obtaine of him for vs, ſo manie great graces and fauours, who is ſo beſide him ſelfe, that he wil not doe honour and reuerence to ſo diligent and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing an aduocatrice.<note n="a" place="margin">Lib de excellen. virg. ca.
<hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>S. Anſelmus</hi> ſaith that the virgin hath ben exalted to ſuch greatnes for vs, to the end ſhe might eaſelie obtaine whatſoeuer
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:6438:50"/>good we needed for our ſowle. And <hi>b S. Auguſtin</hi> teacheth that ſhe doth help vs more,<note place="margin">Serm.</note> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al the other Saincts.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mptio.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> In Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ic. lib. <hi>7.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> fine. Caniſ. lib.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. ca. <hi>8.</hi> &amp;
<hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> So that <hi>c Rupertus</hi> calleth her the mountaine of mountaines, from whence cometh to vs al ſuccour, obtai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned of our ſupreame Lord and maker of al things.</p>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>Points for Meditation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Contemplate how the glorie and greatnes of the virgin
<hi>Marie</hi> in heauen do not make her to be vngetful of her clients in earth, for whome ſhe praieth ſo much the more, how much her charitie is greater, &amp; ſhe neerer to the fountaine of al grace.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Contemplate how the virgin is ſo greatlie beloued and fauoured of god that ſhe doth not onlie obtaine what ſhe demaundeth for vs, but god alſo taketh pleaſure, in ſhewing vs fauour by her meanes.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Conſider likewiſe of this, how much it importeth to be vnder the protection of the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> who is the Queene of heauen ſo puiſſant,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:6438:50"/>and ſo charitable, we being ſo weake and ſo needeful, and remaining in ſo daungerous a baniſhment as we doe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="documents">
                  <head>Documents.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 He that hath charitie, as the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> had, getting vp to dignitie doth not forget thoſe whome he leaft be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 The more vertuous that thou ſhalt be, the more God wil fauour thee: &amp; thou ſhalt more eaſilie, obtaine the graces thou doeſt damaund.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Be thou a true deuoute of the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Marie,</hi> and ſhee wil deliuer thee from the daungers of this trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome life.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:6438:51"/>
               <head>OF THE <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IRGIN Maries ſtature and manners, taken out of auncient and holie fathers.</head>
               <p>THe virgin <hi>Marie</hi> was of a meane ſtature, although ſome be of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion as <hi>Nicephorus</hi> writeth that ſhe was of a little more then a meane ſtature.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icephor.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>2.</hi> hist.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>23.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>iphan.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onſtanti.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>esbyter
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>b. de vita
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ariae.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>edrenus
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> compen
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>io hiſt. Anſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us apud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aniſ. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. ca. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> Her coloure was ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>what more broune then white, and was much like the colour of wheate. Her heare was yellow, yet without art or humaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie. Her eyes were quick &amp; liuelie and of a graue colour, but the apple of her eye was like to an oliue colour. Her eye liddes were decentlie blacke, and ſomwhat bowed: her noſe was meane, her lippes of coral colour, her face ſomthing longe, her hands and fingars long.</p>
               <p>In conuerſation ſhe was affable, and gracious in ſpeeche, yet graue &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt: her talke was litle, and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out neceſſitie: ſhe did honour al moſt
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:6438:51"/>willingly: ſhe was ſhamefaſt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure, without laughing, diſdaine, or anie other perturbation. The holy &amp; famous martyr <hi>S. Ignatius,</hi> who liued at the ſame time the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> did,<note place="margin">In epiſtel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ad Ioan. Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſt.</note> in a certaine epiſtle of his, after he had called her a patterne of penance, and a miſtreſſe of chriſtian religion doth ſaie that from many parts of the world there came ſundrie to ſee her, as if ſhe had bene a celeſtial miracle, &amp; a moſt ſacred ſight: to whome ſhe ſeemed ſo maruailous, that euerie one of them was incredibly glad to haue ſeene her, or ſpoken with her. Amongſt thoſe was that greate
<hi>Dionyſius Areopagita,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apud Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſ. lib
<hi>5.</hi> ca <hi>1.</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mediu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp; fine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in &amp; ca <hi>22.</hi> post prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cip.</note> who being at the maieſtie of the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
<hi>Marie,</hi> and woundering at the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines of her manners, and beholding in her I know not what celeſtial and diuine brightneſſe, did ſay, that if
<hi>Chriſt</hi> had not bene reuealed to him, he would eaſelie haue beleeued that there had bene no other god then the virgin <hi>Marie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Homil. de hypapan. Domini.</note> Hence it is that the holy doctor
<hi>Saint Chryſoſtome</hi> doth cal our
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:6438:52"/>Ladie <hi>the great miracle of the vvorld.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>CERTAINE AVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient miracles vvrought by the virgin Marie.</head>
               <p>VVHat time <hi>Leo Iſauricus</hi> ſought to take awaie holie images out of the church of <hi>Chriſt, S. Iohn Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcene</hi> did write three bookes in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of them: wherewith the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries (of images) being offended, they did accuſe him as a breaker of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces peace, ſaying that he had written letters of treaſon, whereupon his right hand was out of. But <hi>Damaſcene</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into his cloſet, and kneeling downe before the image of oure La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, ſaid in this manner. See heere, o moſt holie mother, how for defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding holie images, my hand hath bene cut of: to thee doe I humblie commend mie ſelfe: which when he had vttered with teares, he ſlept, and in ſleepe did ſee the bleſſed virgin reſtore him his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, ſo that, waking he found his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:6438:52"/>whole: there remayninge onlie a ſigne of the cut. This miracle was moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in al the Eaſt, and written by
<hi>Iohn</hi> Patriarcke of Ieruſalem.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theophilus</hi> Archdeacon in Cilicia, being accuſed by ſome enuious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, was put out of his office, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at the matter did denie <hi>Chriſt</hi> and oure Ladie, and by a certaine writing did giue him ſelf to the diuel, wherunto to he was induced by a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Iew that was a magician. But afterwards repenting him ſelfe, he went into a church of oure Ladie, praying her with teares and faſtings for manie daies and nights, that ſhe would help him. At the length the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> made the writing to be reſtored to him by the diuel, and ſo being reconciled to the Church, he entred into grace with god, and liued in ſuch manner that he was a Sainct, whoſe feaſt is celebrated the 4. daie of februarie. This hiſtorie is written by <hi>Metaphraſtes</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marie</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Aegiptiaca</hi> of Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:6438:53"/>a publicke harlot, going to ſee the churche of the holy Croſſe in Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, would often haue entered, but ſhe could not; whereat aſtonied and touched of god inwardlie, ſhe did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into her ſelfe, and aſhamed of her life, did turne her ſelfe to an image of the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> that ſtoode neere to the church doare and ſaide: O virgin and mother, ſeeing that god, whome thou haſt brought forth, became man therby to cal ſinners to penance, aſſiſt and ſuccour me voide of al helpe: and I doe promiſe, if I enter into this chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, to chaunge my life. She entred &amp; by the virgin <hi>Maries</hi> interceſſion was reconciled to god, and after this reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her ſelfe into the deſert, ſhe did penance, &amp; died a holy woman. This hiſtorie was written by <hi>Paulus Diaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> &amp; is to be reade in the ſecond Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene councel, <hi>actione 4.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the yeare 1094 a certaine woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Laudune was condemned to death for committing a murder ſecreatlie: and as ſhe went to the place of execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:6438:53"/>where ſhe was to be burned, ſhe entred into a church of our Ladie, and there inwardlie contrite did confeſſe her ſinne publiklie, and afterwards weeping ſhe turned her ſelfe to an image of the bleſſed virgin, reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingher helpe for her ſowle, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her ſelf to her with al her hearte, departing that ſhe was fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the church and come to the place of puniſhment, ſhe was twiſe caſt into the mideſt of a great fire, which nether did burne, nor touch her: and that which made the miracle more manifeſt was, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther her garments were as much as touched of the fire, whereat al the people aſtonied, did returne with the woman to the Church, &amp; giue thanks to the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> by whoſe praiers they acknowledge this miracle to haue bene wrought. Thus writeth <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibert</hi> in his chronicle.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neſtorius</hi> was ſtrooken of God with diuers tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,<note place="margin">Caniſ. de. Maria De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>para lib. <hi>3.</hi> ca.
<hi>18.</hi> &amp; lib. <hi>5.</hi> ca.</note> for his blaſphemies vſed againſt the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he amended not him ſelf, his
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:6438:54"/>tongue was cruellie eaten,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp;
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icephor.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>14.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>st. eccl.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>36.</hi>
                  </note> with wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and he did dye moſt miſerablie, whoſe body being buried, the earth did open and ſwallowe it vp. <hi>Moſcus Euiratus</hi> alſo doth write, that when the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> did appeare to the Abbot
<hi>Cyrriacus</hi> in ſleepe, richlie ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and hauing in her companie.
<hi>S. Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> and <hi>S. Iohn Euangeliſt,</hi> he did praie her that ſhe would vouchſafe to enter into his chamber: but ſhe aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him in this manner, How wilt thou that I enter into thie chamber, where thou haſt mine enimie? And with this ſhe departed. The Abbot whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was awaked was verie anxious for that he knewe not who this enimie of the virgin was. But reading a certai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne booke which <hi>Iſichius</hi> prieſt of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem had lent him, he found that in the end thereof with it were bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d twoe bookes of <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> &amp; ſo he ſtraight waies vnderſtood who was the enimie of the virgin, and forthwith burning theſe two bookes, the Abbot was much comforted. Of this euerie one maie ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:6438:54"/>that diſhoneſt bookes alſo be eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> and ſo it is no maruaile, if ſhe do not enter into the chamber of the ſoule of theſe that kepe ſuch bookes. Thus we reade in the booke intituled <hi>Pratum ſpirituale</hi> A ſpiritual medowe. Chap. 46.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregorius Turonenſis</hi> in his booke <hi>de gloria martyrum</hi> doth recount, that a certaine Iews ſonne went to a church of the bleſſed virgin, &amp; there did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with other ſcholars, &amp; retur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning home ioyful that he had ſo done he told his father of it, whoe became ſo enraged at the matter, that being a glaſſe maker he tooke the childe and threw him into the burning for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, heaping more woode, therby the more toe inflame the fornace. The childs mother came running to the place, and when ſhe could not approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che neere to the fornace, for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedinge greate flame that it ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t forth, ſhe cried out, in ſo much that manie people did runne to the howſe where ſhe was, whoe remouing the fire from
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:6438:55"/>the fornace, did find the childe lying as it were in a moſt delicate bead, and asking him how the fire had not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed his bodie, he aunſwered that the woman, at whoſe Alter he had communicated in the morning, did ſtand by him, and defend him from the fire with her mantel. This hiſtorie did <hi>Menna</hi> the Patriarch (as <hi>Glycas</hi> writeth) tel to <hi>Iuſtine</hi> the ſecond Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of that name,<note place="margin">Parte. <hi>4.</hi> Annaliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> as one whoe had bene preſent at the fact.</p>
               <p>When Rome was grieuouſlie vexed with the plague, <hi>S. Gregorie</hi> the greate being at that time Pope, did ordaine a ſolemne proceſſion to be made vpon Eaſter daie, bearing through al the Cittie the image of our Ladie (which is ſaid to be that of <hi>S. Marie maior</hi> yet extant in Rome) whervppon the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue did ceaſe verie miraculouſlie, at the which the people greatlie reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, behold an Angel that did ſing in the ayre, <hi>Regina coeli laetare Alleluya</hi> &amp;c. Queene of heauen reioice Alleluya: for that he whome thou deſeruedſt to
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:6438:55"/>beare Alleluia, is riſen as he ſaid Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luya. And the holy Pope aunſwered, Praie god for vs Alleluia.
<hi>Sigonius</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others doth recount this in his firſt booke
<hi>de regno Italiae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the booke intituled <hi>Pratum ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuale</hi> chap.
<hi>45.</hi> we reade of a certaine monke, who moleſted with a long temtation, ſaide to the diuel, when wilt thou let me be quiet. And the diuel appearing to him ſpake in this manner. Sweare to me, that thou wilt not vtter to anie one that which I ſhal tel thee, and I wil not moleſt thee any more. The mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke did ſweare, and the diuel then ſaide, worſhip no more this image of our Ladie, and I wil let thee alone. The monke tooke time to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate of the matter, &amp; in the meane ſeaſon diſcouered al to his Abbot, who did reprehend him for giuing his oath to the diuel, and afterwards ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted him to worſhip the image of the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> telling him that he had obtained the victorie in ſo greate temptation by the help of the virgin,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:6438:56"/>and that leauing to worſhip her, he ſhould eaſelie be ouercome of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel. Theſe &amp; other miracles wrought by God thorough the interceſſion of the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> are written largelie by <hi>Petrus Caniſius</hi> in his firſt booke of the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> chap. 19. and 20.</p>
               <div type="instruction">
                  <head>An inſtruction hovv to meditate vvel.</head>
                  <p>Take ſome time aſſured &amp; determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate for meditation, which thou muſt not chaunge without iuſt cauſe, for that the diuel, when at the firſt he cannot make thee leaue praier; doth ſeeke to make thee differ it vntil ſome inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modious time, that ſo thou maie make it with many defects, &amp; he more eaſelie perſwade thee afterwards to leaue it altogeather. The time moſt fit is the morning before other affaires, &amp; it is conuenient that we giue the beſt time to this holy exerciſe, ſo grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to god and profitable to our ſowle.</p>
                  <p>Let the place be retired, where no other buſines nor talke maie be heard, which doth cauſe diſtraction, and if thou haue no ſuch place at home thou
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:6438:56"/>muſt not therfore leaue to meditate, but doe of thie part what thou canſt, and afterwards truſt in God, who of his goodnes wil ſupplie with his holie grace, to make thee be recollected.</p>
                  <p>The ſituation of the bodie muſt be modeſt and deuoute, as kneeling or ſtanding: walking ſeemeth not a fit act for meditation, vnles it were little and ſoftlie. And albeit a man ſitting maie meditate without ſinne, yet he ought to chooſe that manner, which doth moſt further him to attention &amp; deuotion ſo that it be without vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and without paine, if ſomtimes thou do meditate ſitting, it is good (if thy health can beare it) to ſtand bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed, in ſigne that thou doeſt not think of other affaires, nor ſtudie or ſpeculate philoſophical matters, but pray and deale with god thy creator.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="step">
                  <head>That vvhich a man must doe before Meditation.</head>
                  <p>The night before meditation thou muſt foreſee the points &amp; miſterie wherof thou muſt meditate in the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:6438:57"/>morning, and when thou doſt wake; or riſe out of thie bedde, thinke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the meditation thou art to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collected and attentiue: and if in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie affaire of oures which we handle with men, we thinke wel of it before we doe it, how much more ought we to doe ſo in this thing which is ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, and whereof we muſt deale with god.</p>
                  <p>When thou wilt goe to the place of meditation, imagine thie ſelfe to be there looked for of <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord, to giue thee grateful audie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; and going praie thyne Angel keeper, or ſome one of thoſe Saints toe whome thou art moſt deuoute, that he wil accompanie thee, and bring thee in to oure Lord. And when thou art come to the place thou muſt doe him moſt humble and deuoute reuerence.</p>
                  <p>As ſoone as thou haſt kneeled doune lift vp thy minde to god, demaunding helpe to make thy meditation to the glorie of his diuine maieſtie, &amp; f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uite of thy ſoule, folowing in this the holie
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:6438:57"/>church, which in the beginning of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſeruice doth ſaie, <hi>Deus in adiuto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium meum intende. Domine ad adiuuan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum me feſtina,</hi> that is. O god be atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue to my ayde. O Lord make ſpeede to helpe me. It doth alſo helpe in the beginning, to craue pardon of god for our imperfections and ſinnes, which are wont to offend his diuine eyes: but thou with repenting thie ſelfe, and as king forgiuenes, ſhalt make him propitious and wel affected towards thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="step">
                  <head>That vvhich a man muſt doe in time of Meditation it ſelfe.</head>
                  <p>TO the end thou be more attentiue to thy meditation, thinke thy ſelfe to be preſent at the miſterie whereof thou doeſt meditate, that thou doe as it were ſee, and heare the perſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined therin, diſcourſing with thie vnderſtanding, not onlie about their woords and deedes, but alſo about that which ſuch perſons might religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlie think of; for this wil giue thee more ample matter of meditation,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:6438:58"/>and make thee much more attentiue.</p>
                  <p>when in anie one point thou feeleſt ſome effect of deuotion, or any other ſpiritual motion, ſeeke not to paſſe ouer ſpeedilie to another point, for it is better for thee that thou arreſt thy ſelfe ſomewhat longer in the former.</p>
                  <p>In meditating, endeuour alwaies to drawe to the affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy wil, that which the vnderſtanding hath found out by diſcourſing: ether by reiecting the ſame, if it be ought belonging to ſinne, or by embracing it with great affection, if it be any thing pertaining to vertue or deuotion, becauſe this is the principal fruite of meditation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="step">
                  <head>That vvhich a man muſt doe, vvhen he hath ended Meditation.</head>
                  <p>IN the end of meditation thou ſhalt make a colloquie or ſpeeche, which is nothinge els but a familiar and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuous talk with God, now praiſing his greatenes: nowe thanking him for his benefits: now asking him pardon for our ſinnes, or perſeuerance in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good: now offering him our life
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:6438:58"/>and woorkes, with a ſtedfaſt purpoſe nether to doe nor thinke anie thinge, that may diſpleaſe his diuine maieſtie.</p>
                  <p>Alſo when meditation is ended, it is profitable to make ſome little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexion vppon the ſame, that ſoe thou maiſt ſee how it hath ſucceeded with thee, and if thou finde anie fault or impediment, thou muſt auoide it for the time to come.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="step">
                  <head>An aduiſe hovv to ouercome ſome difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that fal out in Meditation.</head>
                  <p>THat which chiefelie ought to moue thee to meditation, muſt be a pure and ſyncere deſire, to pleaſe God in this holie exerciſe, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme thie life and manners to the wil of thy maker: for this wil helpe thee verie much to ſurmount ſome difficulties, that haue made manie for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake mental praier.</p>
                  <p>The firſt difficultie is to find thie ſelfe without guſt of deuotion, and ſo drie, that meditation wil not ſeeme onlie a comberſom thing to thee, but alſo time loſt. To ouercome this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:6438:59"/>thou muſt note, that Ariditie or drines maie come ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times of thine owne fault, as when thou haſt no care to prepare thie ſelfe to medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by foreſeeing that which thou art to meditate, according to that which before hath ben ſaide: wherof it commeth that thou doeſt it with negligence and drilie, for that oure Lord in puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of thie reachleſnes, doth woorthelie depriue thee of the conſolation and taſt of meditation. The remedie to be ryd of this pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, is to take awaie the cauſe, which is thy fault.</p>
                  <p>Sometime this Ariditie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thie fault, and thou muſt not for this leaue thie meditation, for as time of conſolation doth pleaſe thee, when our Lord, like the ſunne of the ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, comming neere to thee doeth make thee haue guſt in meditation: ſo thou muſt not be diſpleaſed nor leaue to meditate, when the ſelfe ſame Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, as the ſunne of winter doth goe from thee: that which he alſo doth for
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:6438:59"/>thy good, that then thou maiſt caſt rootes of humility, knowing that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he goeth from thee, thou remaineſt drie and aride.</p>
                  <p>It maie be alſo that he ſuffreth thee to be drie in praier, to ſee if thou be a ſouldiar for loue, or for paiement, which thou doeſt expect of him, as if to praie, thou wouldeſt he ſhould paie thee with guſt of deuotion. Or els god doth this, to make thee know that the taſt and comfort of meditation is his gift, &amp; he giueth it to whom, &amp; when he wil, that by this meanes thou diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thy ſelfe to aske it hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blie of him. Be it howſoeuer, if thou praie therby to pleaſe god, as thou oughteſt to do; thou maiſt ſaie, I did not begin mie meditation to feele guſt, but for the loue of my god, and for his loue wil I followe it on.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond difficultie is to be mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in time of meditation, with diuers and importunate thoughtes, whether they come by woorke of the diuel, to hinder the fruite of meditation, or els
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:6438:60"/>for that our nature being diſordered by ſinne; our imagination goeth wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring againſt our wil, enta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gling it ſelfe with diuers &amp; impertinent thoughts. In this caſe thou muſt be diligent to caſt them of but yet without anxietie, vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding that as lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as they come without thy conſent, it is no ſinne to thee: and the labour in caſting them away to meditate wel, is no leſſe grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to god, then to praie attentiuelie with taſt, yea thou ſhalt merite more, then if thou diddeſt feele great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in praier.</p>
                  <p>It auaileth alſo much in ſuch tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uails to make ſome ſpeeches, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund helpe of god, humblie confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that of thie ſelfe thou canſt not help thee; or reprehending thie ſelfe, that thou canſt not ſtand one hower with thy maker, without ſome earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie cogitation, for ſcrupuls and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations which doe happen in praier, a good remedie is not to eſteeme them, but to be recollected in meditation. Likewiſe when anie buſines of ſmal
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:6438:60"/>importance doth repreſent it ſelfe to be done<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of praier, it is not good to breake of meditation and doe it, or for memories ſake to note it: becauſe meditation being a woorke ſo prefect and ſo acceptable to god, it muſt not for euerie trifling thing be broken, or left of.</p>
                  <p>The third difficultie is, that manie ſeeing no fruite to come of this exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe doe leaue it as a thing vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: but this is a manifeſt tentation, &amp; cometh of not knowing wherein the true fruite of meditation doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, for if thou doe praie becauſe thou loueſt god, thou muſt eſteeme it to be a great benefit for thee, that thou doſt pleaſe him, and vndoubtedlie thou doeſt pleaſe him, euerie time that thou doeſt in meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what thou art able. True it is that toe flie ſinne, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne wel our life, as we ſee in thoſe that with humilitie doe frequent me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, is the proper fruite thereof, and riſeth of that light, which men doe receaue of god in meditation.</p>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:6438:61"/>
                  <p>The fourth difficultie groweth of that we ſee, we doe not obtaine of god what we demaund in praier. But this muſt not remoue thee from medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which thou muſt chiefelie make to praiſe, thanke, and bleſſe god; and muſt thinke it a ſingular benefit to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent meditation, becauſe it is a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly execiſe and grateful to god, whome if thou procure to ſatisfie in this, doubt not but he wil graunt thee more then that, which thou doeſt demaund, if yet it be for the good of thie ſoule.</p>
                  <p>The fift difficultie is, that ſomtimes meditation wil ſeeme tedious to thee. There is no doubt but that the diuel wil repreſent meditation vnto thee as a verie hard thing, ſoe to make thee differ it, and afterwards to forſake it wholie. But if thou haue a true deſire to do a thing acceptable to thie Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, either meditation wil not ſeeme a labourſome thing to thee, or thou wilt holde al labour wel emploied for his loue, who did take ſo great labour and paine for thy ſake.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6438:61"/>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
